<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some generall observations upon Dr. Stillingfleet's book, and way of wrighting with a vindication of St. Ignatius Loyola, and his followers the Iesuits, from the foul aspersions he has lately cast upon them, in his discourse concerning the idolatry, &amp;c. : in four letters, written to A.B.</title>
            <author>Ashby, Richard, 1614-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7040</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12528118</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12528118</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62701</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26001)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62701)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 303:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some generall observations upon Dr. Stillingfleet's book, and way of wrighting with a vindication of St. Ignatius Loyola, and his followers the Iesuits, from the foul aspersions he has lately cast upon them, in his discourse concerning the idolatry, &amp;c. : in four letters, written to A.B.</title>
                  <author>Ashby, Richard, 1614-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 96 [i.e. 69] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Ashby, also known as Richard Thimelby. Cf. Wing; DNB.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [4].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ignatius, --  of Loyola, Saint, 1491-1556.</term>
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699.</term>
               <term>Jesuits.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62701:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Some generall OBSERVATIONS UPON D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>STILLINGFLEET'S</hi> Book, and way of Wrighting.</p>
            <p>WITH A Vindication of St. <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> and his followers the Ieſuits.</p>
            <p>From the foul Aſperſions he has lately caſt upon them, in his diſcourſe concerning the <hi>Idolatry,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In four Letters, written to <hi>A. B</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed, 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62701:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A ſhort addreſs to the READER. concerning Dr.</hi> Stillingfleet, <hi>and his preſent Anſwerers.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WIthout farther ceremony, be pleaſed to take notice that theſe Letters were ready for the Preſs, much about the time, when his Majeſty's gracious Declaration for a general toleration came firſt out a time which was generally thought not ſo ſeaſonable for expoſing ſuch writings to publick view. I was therefore willing to follow the example of other Catholick Writers, who then were unanimouſly reſolved rather to ſmother their juſt complaints in ſilence, and quietly enjoy his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties indulgent favour to all Non Conformiſts; then by juſtifying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, raiſe new heats and animoſities amongst his Majeſties loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Had Proteſtants then been as forward to lay down their armes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably not only theſe Letters would have been ſtill ſuppreſſed; but all other Polemical writings in this kind. But when we heard of a new Warr ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly proclaimed againſt us out of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> by <hi>D. Tillotſon,</hi> and our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries <hi>(Dr. Stilllingfleet</hi> by name) dayly triumphing and inſulting over us, and interpreting this our ſilence to be an argument of our weakneſs, as if his books were unanſwerable; we could no longer forbear to ſpeake for our ſelves without betraying our cauſe.</p>
            <p>Now as <hi>D. Stillingfleet</hi> in particular has abuſed many you are to know that many have been alſo bold to laſh him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and diſcover his tricks, and it is worth your obſervation, that no leſs then eight ſeveral Treatiſes are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy come out againſt his charge of <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Fanaticiſme,</hi> &amp;c. either to the whole Libel or to ſome part of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. D. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> againſt <hi>Dr. Stillingfleet,</hi> in which he is ſhewed to be a very <hi>Lylbourn,</hi> ever jarring with himſelf, and ſcarce able to write ten pages without a manifeſt contradiction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> by the ſame Learned Author that writ <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancy without Principles:</hi> to which the Dr. has been fain to make ſo poor a retourn.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. Containing an entire anſwer to the Drs. whole book, which I hear will ſhortly be made publick, though the greateſt part of it was taken in the Preſs by the Drs. Emiſſaries.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb facs="tcp:62701:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> 4. There is a Collection of 4 other Treatiſes bound together, in anſwer to the material things in the Drs. book, 1. <hi>Fanaticiſme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anatically impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Church of</hi> Rome. 2. <hi>The Roman Church's devotion vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated.</hi> 3. <hi>Of Indulgences.</hi> 4. <hi>His Proteſtant Principles diſcovered.</hi> The firſt of theſe was written by one of thoſe moſt Learned writers that ſent away Dr. <hi>Peirce</hi> with a flea in his ear. The other three were penn'd by the Learned Author of the <hi>Guide in Controverſy.</hi> Theſe Letters make up the eighth Treatiſe and I am credibly informed that the Author of the two queſtions (which in truth are unanſwerable (though the cauſe as the Dr. pretends of the preſent Controverſy) has a full anſwer ready, which I doubt not will be ſuitable to his Worth and Learning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And let not the Dr. ſlight any of theſe Treatiſes, becauſe they are not of ſo great a bulk as his own: for after a diligent peruſal, you will finde, that this mighty Man, who in his own conceit, was ſwel'd up as big as another</hi> Goliah, <hi>profeſſing himſelf to be invincible, has met with as many</hi> David<hi>'s ſlings to fell him to the ground, as there are books out againſt him. If this be not really ſo, let him take up his Buckler, and appear again in the Field to defend himſelf; let him, I ſay, make a cloſe reply to his Adverſaries, and he will ſhew himſelf a man, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, his vapouring will not do it: for he that only challenges his Enemy into the Field, or ſtrikes the firſt ſtroke, and then runs away when he meets with a reſiſtance, ſhall never have the reputation of a ſtout man. It is eaſie enough to make a fair flowriſh in words, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the greateſt Paradox in the VVorld, if there muſt be no ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting into the ſolidity of the Proofs: and it is after this rate that the Dr. writes bookes, without caring how to defend them, when they are once got ſafe out of his hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But now a word or two to his</hi> Rationall Account: <hi>he often brags it has never yet been anſwered, though he knows well, that both the</hi> Guide in Controverſy, <hi>and</hi> Proteſtancy without Principles, <hi>had deſtroyed his very Foundation; nay he knowes that many learned Men of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>have deſpiſed it as no ways advantageous to their cauſe, and deem'd it a Fanatical work, as defending the</hi> Greeks, Arrians, <hi>and all other Hereticks, and Schiſmaticks, that oppoſe the Church of</hi> Rome. <hi>Notwithſtanding all this, had not Mr.</hi> Sp. <hi>dyed and ſeft his work half finiſhed, the Dr. would have ſeen himſelf baffled long a go and it will not be long, I hope, before another Learned hand compleat the Work, to the ſhame and confuſion of this vain and ſelf conceited Man; Farewell, and be ſo kind as to excuſe and correct theſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:62701:3"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge. 1. Sir is omitted in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. p. 7. l. 15. dele much. p. 9. l. 19. <hi>ſermones.</hi> p. 10. l. 3. well, l. 4. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals. p. 14. l. 5. jealous, p. 16. l. 30. dele <hi>alſo,</hi> p. 19. l. 1. <hi>Bozius.</hi> l. 31. for at p. 22. l. 1. makes. l. 12. to the. l. 19. his way. l. 31. carryed away. p. 23. l. 2. time l. 17. and that, p. 25. l. 1 <hi>literae.</hi> l. 6 whereas. p, 26. l. 19. as ſlight. l. 22. expreſſions, p. 27. l. 5. only ſoon, l. 26. of the. l. 27. dele the, and read with a. p. 29. l. 5. dele if, l 34. one of his, p. 34. l 30. witneſſes. p. 35. l. 10. he is not, l. 25. by good. p. 37. l 31, how eaſie. p. 38. l. 9. cites <hi>Navar.</hi> l. 16. titles p. 39, l, 39. neither taught, p, 41, l. 33: the miſdemeanours, p, 42. l. 18. in thoſe l. 23, triple, l, 33, du Pleix, Peter Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, l, 34, <hi>Spondanus.</hi> p, 48. l. 5, and 9, St. <hi>Amour.</hi> p. 52. l. 8. dele that. p. 53. l. 7, ſaw how, l, 20, moſt forward. p. 55. l. 14, of theſe ſome, l, 28. too clear, p. 58, l, 1, dele ſect. 9, and read D, <hi>Stillingf.</hi> ſect. 9, l, 12, for calling, l, 15, executed p, 60, l, 32, contrivance, p, 61, l, 10, that Cardinal, l, 29, was not of, l, 32, delivered it at Port Royal or if, l, 36, talkes of. p, 64, l, 12. <hi>Archivium,</hi> p, 67, l, 17, dele any, p, 68, l, 20, into <hi>Canton.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:62701:3"/>
            <head>THE FIRST LETTER; SOME OBSERVATIONS UPON Dr. STILL<hi rend="sup">ts</hi> BOOK, And way of Writing.</head>
            <p n="1">1. I Have ſpent ſome few hours upon that part of Dr. Still. <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> which was the ſubject of ours lately, and the occaſion of your laſt Letter. And before I enter upon telling you my particular reflexions, you may pleaſe to obſerve three things; the firſt, his ſevere dealing with Roman-Catholicks; the ſecond, his Comical and jeſting way of expreſſing himſelf; the third, his cunning artifices to deceive his Reader.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His ſeverity is the more remarkable, becauſe contrary to the modern ſtile of his own party, and croſs to his own ſentiments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in his <hi>Rational Account,</hi> (p. 1. Ch. 2. &amp; p. 3. Ch. 4. &amp; p. 54.) For there he is ſo complaiſant, as to confeſs (with other Proteſtants) that the Roman Church is a true Church, yea <hi>the very ſame with theirs,</hi> and <hi>a true way to ſalvation,</hi> and that <hi>ſhe holds the foundation,</hi> that is, all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62701:4"/> fundamental or eſſential points of faith, and differs only in certain <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour truths,</hi> or <hi>pious opinions,</hi> which no man is bound to believe. But now (ſince the Lady left his Congregation) he is grown ſo fierce on a ſuddain, there's no dealing with him, he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeds Unchurch us, and by laying <hi>Fanaticiſm</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> at our doors, obſtruct our way to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, leaving us no other gate to Heaven, but that of ignorance or repentance, which lyes open to Turks and Jews as well as Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This makes me call to mind, a pleaſant paſſage between Biſhop <hi>Ferne</hi> and a good honeſt Parſon, of whom I had it. The Parſon was ready to publiſh a moderate Treatiſe in <hi>Grotius</hi> his way; but the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop would by no means ſuffer it to go to the Preſs, but tould the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor that he was very much miſtaken, if he thought that was the way to win us: he muſt know, that <hi>a Papiſt was a kind of a beaſt, that would not be tamed with ſtroaking:</hi> much leſs with ſtriking, ſaid the Parſon. But the Biſhop for all that would not alter his opinion; but the book muſt be ſuppreſſed. Dr. Stillingfleet is directly of the Biſhops mind, he will ſtroake us no more, he will not court us into the ſame Church, or flatter us with the hope of ſalvation, as he has done formerly, he is now all for dry blows, and down right <hi>ſtriking,</hi> and will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with any leſs charge, to beat down Popery, than that of <hi>Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm, Idolatry,</hi> and unavoidable damnation: how in conſequently to his own maximes, you have partly ſeen already, and has been clearly evidenced, in that ſhort but ſmart piece, <hi>Dr. Stillingfleet againſt Dr. Stillingfleet,</hi> where he is made not only to wipe away the dirt, which he had caſt at the Roman Church, but to throw a good part of it in his own face, by manifeſtly proving himſelf an Idolater, by the very ſame arguments which he brought to prove Catholicks guilty of that crime. And the Author (had he bin diſpoſed) could with as much eaſe, have proved him a <hi>Fanatick</hi> as an <hi>Idolater</hi> from the ſame principle he made uſe of againſt Catholicks.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For why I pray are we <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> in his judgement? becauſe forſooth we <hi>countenance</hi> ſome private <hi>revelations,</hi> and allow ſome of our Saints to have had an <hi>Enthuſiaſtick way,</hi> as he calls it, <hi>in their devotions.</hi> Now this argument is far ſhort of proving us <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> becauſe we own nothing in this kind, but what is approved of by the authority of the Church, which is ever watchful and ſevere in puniſhing all impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and will not ſuffer pretended revelations, or any ſuch extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary favours of Allmighty God to paſs for currant, but what have paſt the teſt of a rigorous examination. For it is well known, that all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62701:4"/> ſuch pretenders, are immediately clapt up by the Inquiſition, and do not eaſily recover their liberty, till they have given a good account of themſelves. So that none amongſt us are permitted to be their own judges, in matters of faith, or particular ways of devotion, but all are obliged to ſubmit to the judgement of the Church, and be guided by their lawful Paſtors and Superiours: which ſubmiſſion effectually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys, the very notion of <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> which is grounded in a private Spirit, and independent way of proceeding, contrary to authority.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Yet as to the Doctor, the argument comes home, to prove him a <hi>Fanatick.</hi> For I argue thus: he is a <hi>Fanatick</hi> that pretends to rule himſelf in matters of faith, by his private ſpirit revealing the truth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, but D. Still. pretends to rule himſelf in matters of faith, by his private ſpirit revealing the truth unto him, <hi>ergo</hi> Dr. Stillinfleet is a <hi>Fanatick.</hi> That he that pretends to rule himſelf in matters of faith, by his private ſpirit revealing the truth unto him, is a <hi>Fanatick,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denyed, it contains the very notion of <hi>Fanaticiſm.</hi> The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is evident. The only thing I am to prove is, that the Doctor pretends to rule himſelf in matters of faith, by his private ſpirit reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth unto him. This I evidence out of the Principles ſet down by him, in the end of his Book, <hi>Princ.</hi> 5. where he ſays, <hi>that there can be no other means imagined, whereby we are to judge of the truth of Divine Revelation, but a faculty in us of diſcerning truth and flalſhood, in matters propoſed to our belief, Princ.</hi> 13. That <hi>the Scriptures can be underſtood by all perſons, who ſincerely endeavour to know the meaning of them, Princ.</hi> 14. And that <hi>they contain the whole will of God ſo plainly revealed, that no ſober enquirer can miſs of what is neceſſary for Salvation.</hi> For what I pray can tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>faculty of diſcerning truth from falſhood in matters of faith</hi> avail him, with all the <hi>ſincere endeavours, and ſober enquiry</hi> he ſpeaks of, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be infallibly aſſiſted by ſome private ſpirit, which inſpires and reveals the truth unto him. For ſince it is clear by experience, that the ſame words of Scripture, are conſtrued by others, after all their <hi>endeavours,</hi> and beſt <hi>enquiry</hi> to find out the truth, in a quit different ſenſe from that, in which the Doctor underſtands them, he muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſome ſuch private infallible aſſiſtance, which others have not. For example, the Doctor underſtands his commandments ſo, that God has there forbidden all worſhip of Images; Catholicks underſtand them otherwiſe, ſo as to hold ſuch worſhip lawful. The Doctor will have, <hi>This is my body,</hi> to be taken in a Metaphorical ſenſe, and ſo denies the real preſence. Catholicks underſtand it litteraly as it ſounds, and therefore adore Chriſt in the Sacrament. Again an Arrian denies
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62701:5"/> the Son of God to be equal to his Father, and thinks he has clear Scripture for it. <hi>John</hi> 14. 28. <hi>The Father is greater than I.</hi> An Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt will not allow Infant-baptiſm, becauſe, ſays he, the Scripture requires that all be taught before they be baptized, <hi>(Matt.</hi> 18. 19.) <hi>Teach all nations baptizing them,</hi> and children are not capable to be taught. The Doctor reads the ſame Texts, and holds the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary tenets to both. The queſtion then is, how he comes to ſee more than his Neighbours, if he hit right, in all theſe points wherein he differs from <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and other Sectaries, ſince the ſame clear light of Scripture is expoſed to all, be they Catholicks, Arrians, Anabaptiſts, as well as to the Doctor: But oh ſays the Doctor, I have <hi>a faculty in me of diſcerning truth from falſhood, I ſeriouſly endeavour and ſoberly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire</hi> into the truth. They reply, they are rational creatures as well as he, and conſequently have the ſame <hi>diſcerning faculties;</hi> they have alſo ſouls to be ſaved as well as he, and are therefore as much concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>ſerious</hi> in enquiring out, that true faith which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation; they have the ſame promiſes made them, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſiſted in their endeavours, where then is the difference, or how come they all to erre more than the Doctor? will you know the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery? 'tis this: The <hi>faculty</hi> which the Doctor hath of <hi>diſcerning</hi> truth from falſhood, with his <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>ſerious enquiry</hi> has an extraordinary private aſſiſtance, (which others want) and this directs him ſo infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that <hi>he cannot miſs.</hi> What's this in plain Engliſh, but to rely upon I know not what infallible private ſpirit, or to pretend to an <hi>Enthuſiaſtick way</hi> of expounding the Scriptures, when the ſenſe is in diſpute. Is not this to make himſelf (and every Proteſtant) more then Pope? Is it not a degree of <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> equal to the <hi>ſpirit of diſcerning,</hi> which the greateſt <hi>Fanatick</hi> or <hi>Quaker</hi> ever pretended? and after this, me thinks, he ſhould leave of clamouring ſo much againſt new revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſince he has them at his command.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But do you not wonder, Sir, why the Doctor has ſo little cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as to engroſs and monopolize this <hi>enthuſiaſtick</hi> guift of diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true faith, to himſelf and a handful of Proteſtants. Biſhop <hi>Taylour</hi> was a greater <hi>latitudinarian</hi> then ſo, when he granted the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of prophecying</hi> to all Chriſtians. And he was as charitable, in clearing us from <hi>Idolatry,</hi> though the Doctor obſerves well, that elſe where he was of another opinion, that is contradicted himſelf, which he thinks a very ſufficient way of anſwering his arguments, and poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he may uſe the ſame method to defend himſelf, by ſhewing us that in another book he taught otherwiſe. I can aſſure you Sir, it were to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62701:5"/> be wiſhed, that the Dr. had, that which <hi>Momus</hi> found wanting in the bull, <hi>viz.</hi> an eye upon his horn, for he ſtrikes at no aime, and never minds, whether the blow may not light upon himſelf.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I have done with his <hi>ſeverity,</hi> onely I cannot but take notice; how he labours in his Preface, to juſtiſie it, at leaſt for as much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns his charge of <hi>Idolatry</hi> layed againſt us by producing other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Doctors, who managed it againſt us with as much heat, in Q. Elizabeths, and King James his days, for what is all this to the purpoſe, but onely to tell us, that Proteſtants claſh with one another, in this point as well as in others, and that for his part, he is reſolved to ſide with thoſe, that are the moſt rigid and puritanical, ſuch as Dr. Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, whom he rancks in his liſt of Authors, and ſcorns to be leſs zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, ſo that you may probably expect, that his next work will be, to prove the Pope Antichriſt. But ſince he leans ſo much upon the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of his Proteſtant Predeceſſours, I hope he will find a time alſo, to vindicate them from playing the <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> or falſe Prophets, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to foretel, the down ſall of Popery in the year 666. from the number of the beaſt in the Apocalyps. And leaſt Proteſtants ſhould alſo be taken for <hi>viſionairs,</hi> he may do well to give us his opinion of his great grand-father <hi>Luthers</hi> black familiar, <hi>[Luth. to.</hi> 7. <hi>Witt. fol.</hi> 228. <hi>Hoſpin. hiſt. Sacram. p. ult. fol.</hi> 131.] who in a long conference, related by himſelf, gave him ſeveral reaſons for the aboliſhing of the Maſſe, and of Zuinglius <hi>[Zuing. to.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 249.] his private admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher, who as he confeſſes, gave him the ſame counſel, though he did not well remember, whither he were white or black.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I come now to his comical ſtrain of writing, which I little dreamt to have met with, after ſuch a ſober declaration in his Preface, that <hi>nothing ſhall proceed from him, but what becomes a fair and ingenious adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary;</hi> that <hi>he does not think it ſuch a mighty matter, to throw dirt in a mans face, and then to laugh at him,</hi> or, <hi>any great skill, to make things appear ridiculous or dark.</hi> That <hi>it ſhews far more art and ingenuity to give them their due colours, and ſet them in their cleareſt light.</hi> That <hi>ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of expreſſion ſeems to be like throwing of vinegar upon hot coals, which gives a quick ſcent, for the preſent, but vaniſhes immediately into ſmoake and air.</hi> And laſtly, <hi>that though men cannot command their judgements, they may and ought to do their expreſſions.</hi> I ſay after all theſe affected promiſes, of writing ſoberly in the Preface, who would have imagined, to have found either ſo much bitterneſs, or ſo much drollery in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe, or ſo much confidence in the man, as to bind them up both together in the ſame Book. It is a folly to bring inſtances,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62701:6"/> the whole work is ſtuffed with flirts and jeers, which do well in <hi>Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras,</hi> but are nothing becoming a perſon of his calling, or one that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes himſelf <hi>a fair and ingenious adverſary.</hi> This appears chiefly in his fourth Chapter: where he is ſo far from <hi>commanding his expreſſions,</hi> that he makes it his whole buſineſs, <hi>to throw dirt</hi> and make all things <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous,</hi> not ſparing the very Saints themſelves, for whom the greateſt part of Chriſtendom, has ſo much veneration, but making them paſs for the verieſt Idiots and <hi>Fanaticks</hi> in the World. This is not ſuch <hi>a mighty matter</hi> to brag of, ther's <hi>no great skill</hi> in it, for nothing is ſo holy but may be eaſily profaned, by a looſe libertine pen. How ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous might he make the lives of the Prophets, or of St. John Baptiſt, or of Chriſt himſelf, would he but employ his talent in writing them, with as much ſmartneſs and picquancy, as he has done the lives of ſome of our renowned Saints. What can be written in a graver ſtyle, then the life of St. Ignatius of Loyola, is done, by Orlandinus, Maffeius, and Ribadeneira, and yet by his legerdemain, he has ſo metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos'd it, that it appears to be a kind of Romantick ſtory. Take but off his dreſs, and unmask it, <hi>give but things their due colours,</hi> and <hi>ſet them in their clear light,</hi> and you'l find him ſtill a <hi>glorious Saint,</hi> though painted by the Doctor like an <hi>errant Fanatick.</hi> To ſhew this ſhall be the ſubject of my next Letter, where (to uſe his own compariſon) you ſhall ſee, that all <hi>the vinegar, he has cast upon hot coals, vaniſhes imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately into ſmoake and air.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. The third thing I obſerve, in his way of writing controverſies, is his cunning ſhuffling, to deceave the world, for never Mountebank had more devices, to bring about his ends, then this man has tricks, to cozen his Reader, either by miſconſtruing his Authors meaning, or by foiſting in words of his own coyning, in the ſame character with the Text, to make it ſpeak his pleaſure, or chopping in a Parentheſis for his purpoſe, to turn the Readers fancy that way, which he would have him look, or crying up objections without taking any notice of the ſolutions, and ſo condemning the party without hearing his cauſe, or by boldly charging a whole body, with the faults of a few members, though condemned by the major part. Theſe are ſome of the Drs. ſlights, to confute his Adverſaries, and you will diſcover more in the peruſal of his books, for I will not enlarge my ſelf upon them at this preſent. Only I pray take notice, that all this while his deſign is, (as he tels us in his Preface) <hi>to report faithfully</hi> and <hi>to argue cloſely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. I wiſh, Sir, you heard as I do, how ſome judicious Proteſtants expreſs themſelves, concerning this his manner of writing, for I ſhould
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62701:6"/> tire you to relate all their cenſures. One ſays it is the language of a John Potage, and that the only place for ſuch a book in a Library, is amongſt the Comedians and Play books; another that he talks at no aime like a Puritan, and is too ſevere and uncharitable. For my part, I rather pitty the man, than quarrel with his book; I deplore the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of mortals, who are ſo eaſily corrupted with errours and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with paſſions. Yet I cannot but admire, how ſome men can put on the nature of Serpents, and make it their buſineſs, to ſhew their teeth, and bite others. But enough of this ſubject. I am <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="letter">
            <head>THE SECOND LETTER; How the life of St. Ignatius of Loyola is abuſed by Doctor Still.</head>
            <p n="1">1. YOu ſhall ſee in this Letter, how ſhamefully Dr. Still abuſes St. Ignatius, and I am very much confident, you will be of my opinion, that there never was a <hi>Book</hi> ſo belyed the <hi>Preface</hi> as his does, never man that had leſs <hi>command</hi> over his <hi>expreſſions,</hi> or that took it to be <hi>ſuch a mighty matter, to throw dirt in a mans face, and then laugh at him,</hi> as he, whatſoever he there pretends to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Grave Authors have obſerved, that St, Ignatius began the great work, of founding the Society of JESUS, much about the time, that Luther fell into open rebellion againſt the Roman Catholick Church, as if God would tell us, by the circumſtance, that as in the riſe of other Sectaries, he always carefully provided ſtout Champions to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter them, and defend his Church: as S. Athanaſius againſt Arrius, S. Auſtin againſt Pelagius, S. Cyril againſt Neſtorius, S. Hierom againſt Jovinian, Heluidius and Vigilantius, S. Norbert againſt Tanchelinus, St. Dominick and St. Francis againſt the Albigenſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo in theſe later times, he raiſed St. Ignatius and his followers againſt Luther and his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62701:7"/> Camerades, between whom there has ever ſince been an eternal and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconciable feud. And this may be the chief cauſe, why Dr. St. (who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives his negative Religion, from no other ſource) has ſuch a tooth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Jeſuits, and their holy Founder. How groundleſs his plea is againſt the Jeſuits, you ſhall ſee by the next Poſt, <hi>[the third Letter]</hi> my preſent task ſhall be only to ſhew you, how ſhamefully he abuſes ſo great a Saint as Ignatius is, in the common repute of the Chriſtian world; I can aſſure you, there are ſober Proteſtants, that do not love, to ſee him treated with ſo much profaneneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I do not queſtion but you have admired to ſee what a ſtrange metamorphoſis the Author of <hi>Virgil Traveſty</hi> has made of that moſt excellent heroical Poem, and how ridiculouſly it looks under that dreſs, which he has put upon it. This will make you wonder the leſs, to ſee ſo admirable a life, as that of St. Ignatius, made ſo ridiculous, by a malicious and ſcoffing writer, who becauſe he finds no ſuch extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary favours of Allmighty God, in thoſe of his flock, cannot ſee them in the ſervants of God, without laughing at them, as N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ro and Julian the Apoſtat did in their times. And firſt to his <hi>Sect</hi> 12.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His malice here, aimes chiefly at this [<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 4 <hi>Sect.</hi> 12.] to make the Saint paſs for a mere <hi>Alumbra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o,</hi> or one of the Sect of the <hi>Illuminati,</hi> And firſt ſays he, <hi>[l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>] <hi>Maffeius does not deny, that it was upon the account of the Illuminati and his enthuſiaſtical Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſtreets that he was queſtioned in Spain.</hi> By his favour, <hi>Maffejus</hi> has nothing <hi>of his enthuſiaſtical preaching,</hi> (they are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> words of his own coining.) He tells us that it was upon the account of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> as well as the <hi>Illuminati,</hi> that he was brought into ſuſpicion, which (if it prove any thing againſt him) moſt prove him a Lutheran as well as an Alumbrado, and conſequently is impertinent to the Ds. purpoſe. But is a bare ſuſpicion enough to make a man criminal; or does Maffejus or any good Author, give evidence that he was found guilty? quite contrary: all he ſays is, that many were ſuddenly converted to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life, by his good inſtructions, in the Chriſtian faith, and other pious diſcourſes, even in the ſtreets (I hope there is no <hi>Fanaticiſm</hi> in all this) and that this drew the eyes of many upon him, eſpecially in a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous time, when many Sectaries were ſtirring, ſo that upon ſuſpicion, he was called in queſtion, but that after many ſtrict examinations and tryals, not the leaſt fault could be found in his life and Doctrine. By which you ſee, Maffejus his evidence is point blanck againſt him. His next proof is out of the character of the <hi>Illuminati,</hi> which he would faſten upon S. Ignatius, but with as ill ſucceſs. For firſt Ludovicus de
<pb facs="tcp:62701:7"/> Paramo deſcribes them, <hi>by their pride and diſobedience to their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, by their obſtinate adhering to their illuſions, and indulging themſelves in their ſenſual luſts.</hi> Now it is manifeſt, out of the whole courſe of his bleſſed life, that there could not be a more <hi>humble, obedient,</hi> docil and tractable perſon then Ignatius, nor does he commend any thing more to his followers, than <hi>obedience</hi> to their Superiours and ſpiritual guides, as the ſafeſt way to avoid <hi>illuſions,</hi> of which ſubject he has left written a moſt admirable Epiſtle. And as for <hi>ſenſual luſts,</hi> his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation was ſo Angelical, after his converſion, that I defie his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt enemies to find the leaſt blemiſh in that kind. What <hi>Spondanus</hi> adds to the deſcription of the <hi>Illuminati, that under pretence of mental prayer, they deſpiſed the uſe of the Sacraments, preaching the Word of God, and all holy exerciſes,</hi> doth as little ſuit with <hi>Ignatius</hi> his ſpirit, for though he ſtood much for <hi>mental prayer,</hi> as more profitable than <hi>vocal,</hi> if a right uſe be made of it, yet he was a great friend of <hi>Preaching,</hi> and this the Doctor ſhould not deny, who is ever and anon bringing him preaching before his time, and in the very ſtreets, though his Authors at moſt ſpeak of Catechiſtical inſtructions, for he muſt know, that <hi>Sermons</hi> in Latine, does not neceſſarily ſignifie <hi>Sermons</hi> as he always tranſlates it, but familiar diſcourſes. For <hi>the uſe of Sacraments,</hi> it is well known, that St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was ſo far from <hi>deſpiſing</hi> it, that he was not onely a great frequenter of the Sacraments himſelf, but is held to have been the chief Author of reintroducing that pious practiſe, which was much gone to decay before his time. What ſhall I ſay of other <hi>holy exerciſes:</hi> though he loved prayer, yet he had ſo much zeal of ſouls, that he neglected no charitable office, which he could do for the good of his neighbour, either in ſoul or body, witneſs his laying hold of all occaſions, to exhort his neighbour to the deteſtation of vice, and love of vertue, his ſerving the ſick in Hoſpitals, and begging alms for the relief of poor people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You ſee, Sir, not any one part of the character of the <hi>Illuminati</hi> can be applyed to St. <hi>Ignatius;</hi> ſo unlucky is the Dr. in his arguments, as if he took pleaſure in throwing dirt, though it fall ſhort and cannot reach his adverſary. Now if you have a mind to ſee the true character of an Orthodox Chriſtian, in oppoſition to the <hi>Illuminati</hi> and other impure Sects, read over thoſe moſt excellent rules, which St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> has ſet down in the end of his Spiritual exerciſes, <hi>[Reg. ut cum Eccleſia ſentiamus.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 The Doctor will not let this fall ſo, but to <hi>put the matter out of diſpute,</hi> brings in <hi>Melchior Canus,</hi> a <hi>perſon,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of more learning and judgment then a thauſand Ignatius's.</hi> Compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſons are odious, yet
<pb facs="tcp:62701:8"/> let me tell him, St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> has the general repute of a wiſe man; even amongſt Proteſtants, who have lookt well into his Inſtitute, and it is wels known how Catholicks eſteem him. To omit Popes and Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal (who when occaſion ſerves, know how to diſtinguiſh an Engliſh Quaker, from a man in his wits,) <hi>[Orland. l.</hi> 16. <hi>n.</hi> 129.] <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the firſt King of the <hi>Romans</hi> had a great value for him, and <hi>John</hi> the third King of <hi>Portugal</hi> (no fool) thought him the fitteſt man in the world to ſucceed <hi>Julius</hi> the Third in the Chair of St. <hi>Peter.</hi> But to return to <hi>Canus,</hi> he would never believe otherwiſe, but that St. <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> &amp; his companions, were the fore-runners of Antichriſt, deſcribed by the Apoſtle in the laſt times. [2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>to the</hi> 8.] But in this I am ſure he ſhewed neither <hi>learning</hi> nor <hi>judgment.</hi> For firſt a very little learning would have ſerved, to anſwer himſelf with the very ſame ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which St. <hi>Thomas</hi> uſed, <hi>[S. Tho. lib. contra impugn. Relig. c.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25.] to wipe off the like aſperſions from his own Order. Nor does it argue much judgement, to be ſo ſingular and extravagant in his opinion, as to condemn an Order, which was confirmed by the Sea Apoſtolick, and approved by his own whole Order. For not onely <hi>Penna,</hi> a grave Doctor of the ſame Univerſity and Convent with <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> ſtood up in defence of St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> and his Society, but <hi>Franciſcus Romaeus,</hi> General of the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> write a circular Letter, to all his Subjects, in which he not only commends the Fathers of the Society, but commands them in vertue of holy obedience, not to write or ſpeak ill of them, but defend them as their fellow labourers in Chriſts Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, as the Doctor might have ſeen in <hi>Orlandinus, [Hiſt. Soc. Jeſul.</hi> 8. <hi>n.</hi> 46.] in the very place he quotes out of him, but it was not that he lookt for. To his Text out of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> it agrees no more with St. <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> and his followers then his character of the <hi>Illuminati,</hi> but may well be applyed to his grand Patriarck <hi>Luther,</hi> who was a great <hi>lover</hi> of himſelf, <hi>covetous, haughty, proud, blaſphemous and wicked, without peace, incontinent, unmerciful, a lover of voluptuouſneſs more then of God, one that entered</hi> into a Religions <hi>Houſe,</hi> and <hi>lead captive a ſilly</hi> Nun <hi>laden with ſins,</hi> &amp;c. The ſtory he relates, how <hi>Ignatius boaſted of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> in preſence of <hi>Canus,</hi> and <hi>commended one of his brethren for a Saint,</hi> who was Frantick in a certain <hi>conjunction of the Moon,</hi> may go wirh the reſt, upon <hi>Schioppius</hi> his credit (who is as good an Author as <hi>du Moulin)</hi> but will never be credited, by any ſober perſons, who take not the Saint for a ſtarck fool.</p>
            <p>What he adds of St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his flying out of <hi>Spain,</hi> for fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing layed hold on by the Inquiſition, and of his being abſolved at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62701:8"/> for want of accuſers, is as falls as you ſhall ſee anon, for he was both clapt up in the Inquiſition, and honourably diſmiſſed, before he left <hi>Spain, [N.</hi> 20.] and the malice of his accuſers was not wanting at <hi>Rome,</hi> nor the juſt Judgments of God upon them. <hi>[N.</hi> 29.] Yet the Dr. draws out of theſe teſtimonies this wonderful concluſion: <hi>See from what man, the Jeſuits derive the infallibility of their Faith.</hi> I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in what <hi>conjunction of the Moon,</hi> the Doctor writ this, for there never was ſuch a piece of non-ſenſe, as to make the Jeſuits fetch the infallibility of their faith from St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who profeſs as all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks do, that they derive it, from the infallible Word of God propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed unto them by the Catholick Church. I have heard ſome laugh heartily at this paſſage. <hi>This</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>is that which we call pure non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, we muſt confeſs others are but bunglers in compariſon of him, you muſt ſometimes turn over a whole Book before you can find it out, but here it lyes ſo cloſe together, you need not go far to ſeek it. He has the true knack of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. I have done with his <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. ſure in the next, we ſhall have ſomething in good earneſt, if he remember his promiſe, <hi>p.</hi> 262. to prove St. <hi>Ignatius as great a Fanatick as ever has been in the world,</hi> and we ſhall have fair dealing, if he keep his word: for he promiſes to bring no more <hi>Schioppius's</hi> for witneſſes, but only three Jeſuits. <hi>I ſhall only</hi> (they are his words) <hi>make uſe of thoſe of his own Order, who have writ his life, Maffejus, Orlandinus, and Ribadeneira,</hi> he means, ſo he may uſe them after his own faſhion, for as I told you in my firſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he has more tricks than one, to compaſs his ends. And firſt it is not without deſign, that he ſlips over the Saints noble extraction, from the Grandees of <hi>Spain,</hi> both by his Fathers and his Mothers ſide, and his education at Court, for perſons well born and bred, do not uſe to turn <hi>ſneaking Quakers,</hi> and therefore he did prudently to conceal theſe circumſtances, leaſt his Readers fancy ſhould at firſt ſight be drawn off, to imagine him ſomething better than a <hi>quaking Fanatick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. He therefore begins his Hiſtory of St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his life, from his happy converſion, which as all Authors agree was in this manner. In the defence of the Caſtle of <hi>Pampelona</hi> (which was committed to his charge) he received a dangerous wound, which tyed him faſt to his bed, and kept him long under the Chirurgeons hands. Wherefore to paſs away the time, he call'd for ſome profane Book, as his cuſtom was, but the ſpecial providence of God had ſo ordained, for his good, and the ſalvation of many ſouls, that no Book could be found in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62701:9"/> houſe, but the life of Chriſt, and the lives of the Saints. For upon the peruſal of theſe two Books, his heart was filled with thoughts of eternity, and withal ſo inflamed with the love of God, that he was inſtantly changed into another man, and reſolved to follow a new courſe of life, in imitation of Chriſt and his Saints. Tell me, Sir, I pray what do you ſee in this converſion, that may not become a Saint? <hi>[Conf. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 6.] was not St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelf moved with the like ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain converſion of two Courtiers, upon reading St. <hi>Antony</hi> the Ermits life, written by St. <hi>Athanaſius?</hi> yet the Dr. ſticks not here to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare him to <hi>Don Quixot,</hi> and the Books he read to the <hi>old Romances,</hi> onely to cover his profaneneſs, he purpoſely conceals the life of Chriſt, of which the Authors he profeſſes to follow, make expreſs mention. After this to make himſelf more ſport, though at his own coſt, as you ſhall ſee by and by, he ſeems to wonder, how he did to read the Books, which were brought him; for <hi>Maffejus,</hi> ſays he, deſcribes him, as one <hi>that had hardly ever learnt his Letters:</hi> Were this ſo, <hi>Maffejus</hi> had ſoon forgot himſelf, for in his third Chapter, he relates how <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> a little while after, being grown to be a convaleſcent, took a great deal of pains, to write out in a curious hand, in golden and other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured letters, all the remarkable paſſages, which he had obſerved in the life of Chriſt and his Saints, a clear argument, that he knew his Letters well, ſince he could both write and read. But the miſtake is not in <hi>Maffejus,</hi> but in the Doctor, who either does not, or will not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him <hi>Maffejus</hi> his words are: <hi>Literis vixdum a limine ſalutatis;</hi> which every <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Schollar will Engliſh thus: having hardly learnt his Accidence, or being but a very mean Schollar; for they'l tell him, <hi>litera</hi> is not always taken for the Chriſt-croſs row, but moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly for learning: ſo that the Doctor needed not to have turn'd him back, as he does, to his Horn-book. Nor was St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> then ſuch an ignorant ſoul, as he would make him for <hi>Maffejus</hi> obſerves, <hi>[l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2.] that he had long before this, made an heroical Poem in honour of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to whom he was always much devoted. So much crys the Doctor, that it is poſſible it was St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that taught him to read, when he appeared to him; and ſo puts off that viſion with a jeer. And he ſcoffs as much, at his ſtirring himſelf up to perfection, by the example of thoſe two illuſtrious Founders, St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> and St. <hi>Francis,</hi> borrowing metaphors from Knight-errantry to expreſs it ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly, as he does all the reſt; as if it were not a thing very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, to ſtrive to follow the examples of the Saints <hi>[Conf. l.</hi> 8. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 11. The great St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> is not aſhamed to confeſſe; it was the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62701:9"/> example of others, that moved him to a chaſt life. <hi>Canſt thou not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form that, which is perform'd by ſo many of both ſexes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. One night St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> gets out of his bed, falls down upon his knees before an Image of the Bleſſed Virgin, and there wholy devotes himſelf to Gods ſervice, in a new Spiritual warfare under Chriſts Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, what can be more ſerious and devout than this? yet the Dr. is not much taken with this <hi>fit of zeal,</hi> (as he calls it) for he cannot well underſtand what he mean't, to leave his warm bed to pray in the night, and therefore to make this paſſage ſeem alſo ridiculous and Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, he tells us, it was <hi>in that poſture</hi> that he <hi>vow'd himſelf her,</hi> (the Bleſſed Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gins) <hi>Knight,</hi> and has the face to quote <hi>Orlandinus</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badeneira</hi> for it, <hi>[Ribad. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Orland. l.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 12.] who have no ſuch matter. But they both take notice of the ſtrange noiſe and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of the room, where the Saint made this heroical reſolution, of leaving the world in good earneſt, and look upon it as an argument, that his prayer was heard, as it happen'd in the caſe of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, [Acts</hi> 16. 26.] or that the Devil took his leave of him. To this the Dr. only ſays, <hi>there is ſome reaſon to doubt it.</hi> But his doubting will not make St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> a Fanatick:</p>
            <p n="3">3. Soon after this, he had a gracious viſit from the Mother of God, who appear'd to him, with little Jeſus in her arms; at which fight he was wonderfully comforted, and incouraged in his good reſolutions, and particularly in that of leading a chaſt life, and the event prov'd it a true viſion, for from that inſtant, to the hour of his happy departure, he enjoy'd a moſt perfect guift of Angelical purity, both in body and mind. Here the Doctor makes a learned note, in a Parentheſis, <hi>(that he thought himſelf a wake)</hi> for he would have you take it for a dream. But if his friends <hi>Luthor</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> could ſee their black and white ſpirits, while they were broad awake; why may not Gods ſervants have their viſions too, without dreaming. And let me tell him here once for all, that when ſuch viſions are recorded by good Authors, he muſt give us leave to believe them with a moral and humane faith. For as it argues a great deal of folly to believe all things in this kind raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and without good proof; ſo it is an argument of a kind of ſtupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and profaneneſs, to queſtion all ſuch ſtories in the lives of Saints, which upon the Authors credit and due examination, are generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, and cannot rationally be denyed, unleſs we will tye Gods hands, from communicating his favours unto his Saints, who<hi>'s delight is to be with the ſons of men.</hi> It is ſtrange how inconſequently Prot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants proceed in this point. They will ſooner believe that <hi>Tarquin</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62701:10"/> cut a whetſtone with a knife, that <hi>Claudia</hi> a Veſtal Virgin drew a great Ship with her girdle, which could not be ſtirred, and other ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies recounted by <hi>Livy;</hi> than a miracle Canonically examined, and atteſted by many Catholick witneſſes upon Oath.</p>
            <p n="10">10. By this time St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his elder brother, was grown zealous of his intentions of leaving the world, nor was it poſſible for him to conceal them, his very look, his pious diſcourſes, and his continual prayer were enough to betray him. He ſets himſelf therefore to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him, not to diſgrace his noble family, by running upon I know not what extravagant courſes, not to ruine his own fortune and ſuffer all his fair hopes of preferment, purchaſed by his valour with the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life, in the ſervice of his King and Countrey, to be thus blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Bud. But all his Rethorick would not do, St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation proof, againſt all his Batteries, he ſoon ſhook him off, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derpretence of a viſit, which he was to give the Duke of <hi>Noyara,</hi> which he ſoon diſpatcht, he went thence immediately to <hi>Montſerrat,</hi> a place of great devotion to our Bleſſed Lady. In the way thither, entering into diſcourſe with a Moore, who denyed her to have been a Virgin after the birth of her ſon, his z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gan to riſe againſt him, and having yet ſome Reliques left of his Martial ſpirit, he was in ſome d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpute with himſelf, whether he ought not to defend her honour with hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sword, but the Moore being gone another way, in great perplexity, not being able to reſolve the caſe, he puts the Reins in the Mules neck, with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to purſue the Moore, if the Mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> followed at the parting of the two ways and not otherwiſe. But Alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghty God ſo diſpoſed, that the Mule left the beat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n road, and went on difectly to <hi>Montſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi> This certainly was an ignorant piece of zeal, or a pious kind of ſimplicity, in a new convert (for no body goes about to excuſe it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe) only the Authors of his life, note well with St. <hi>Auſtin, [l.</hi> 22. <hi>Cont. Fauſt. c.</hi> 70. that there are ſouls, who even in their vices, ſhew the great capacity and inclination they have to vertue. So <hi>Moyſes</hi> in killing the <hi>Aegyptian, [Exod.</hi> 2.] ſhewd what zeal he was to have for Gods cauſe, and I hope the Dr. will forbear to liſt him in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Fanaticks</hi> for that fact.</p>
            <p n="11">11. It was in his way to <hi>Montſerrat,</hi> that he made a vow of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual chaſtity, and a purpoſe to go in Pilgrimage to <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> Wherefore to put himſelf in a habit ſuitable to that journey, and to the ſevere life he meant to lead, at a Village near the Town, he got him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a rough long coat of Sack-cloath, with a cord to gird it about him, a Pilgrims ſtaff and bottle, and hung them at the pummel of his Saddle,
<pb facs="tcp:62701:10"/> 
               <hi>for fear the people ſhould think him in his wits</hi> (ſays the Doctor in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis) but <hi>Maffejus</hi> (from whom he took that circumſtance) more religiouſly ſays, he did it, that he might by degrees learn not to bluſh at Chriſts poverty.</p>
            <p n="12">12. No ſooner was he come to <hi>Montſerrat,</hi> but he goes ſtraight to the Monaſtery, and there ſpends three whole days, in making an exact general Confeſſion of his whole life, to one of the Religious, to whom he alſo communicated the new courſe of life, he was reſolv'd to lead. After this he hangs up his Sword and Dagger at our bleſſed Lady's Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, puts on his Pilgrims Weed, and ſteals privately out, to give away his rich cloths to a needy Beggar: then return's to the Altar, and there watches and prays all night, (it being the eve of the Annunciation of the Bleſſed Virgin) ſometimes ſtanding, ſometimes kneeling, and all the while zealouſly offering himſelf to Gods ſervice, under the ſpecial Patronage of his Virgin Mother. And the Authors of his life obſerve, that he did this, not to be leſs fervent in conſecrating himſelf to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Militia of Chriſt our Saviour, then the ancient Knights were, who before their Inſtalment were wont to watch in the Church all night in their Arms. Now you ſhall hear what the Doctor ſays to all this. Firſt he warily omits his general Confeſſion and conſulting with his Ghoſtly Father about his leaving the World, as no neceſſary cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in point of Chivalry; then he fondly deſcribes his habit putting <hi>a plain Crab tree-ſtaff</hi> in his hand, and <hi>a wicker ſhooe</hi> on his foot, (for ſo he ignorantly tranſlates <hi>baculus tornatilis</hi> and <hi>calceus eſparto)</hi> and becauſe he is reſolv'd to make him our Lady's Knight, as before in his other night prayer, he made him to <hi>vow himſelf her Knight,</hi> ſo now he repreſents him, <hi>devoting himſelf with all his might to her ſervice,</hi> as if he had not with all entirely conſecrated himſelf unto Almighty Gods ſervice. But that in which he hugs himſelf moſt, is by a certain ſlight of hand, which is natural to him, to pervert his Authors ſenſe, and make the world believe, that the Knights which they ſay, St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> propoſed for his imitation in his night watch, were <hi>Don Quixots;</hi> whereas it is manfeſt that they ſpeak of certain Chriſtian Knights, who it ſeems according to the Ceremonies of their Order, were wont to keep a nights watch in the Church before their Inſtalment.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Thus accouſtred in his Pilgrims Weed, bare-headed, and with but one ſhooe upon that Leg which was lately broken at <hi>Pampelona,</hi> leaving his Mule to the Monks, <hi>early in the morning</hi> (a neceſſary cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance cryes the Dr.) and ſo it was for his purpoſe of concealing himſelf, away he goes for <hi>Manreſa,</hi> a place where he was utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known,
<pb facs="tcp:62701:11"/> there he takes up his lodging in the common Hoſpital, and for that he had been over curious in combing his hair, and tricking up himſelf, he begins now quite to neglect himſelf: lets his hair and nails grow, begs from door to door, faſts every day but Sunday (when he conſtantly went to the Sacraments) Diſciplins himſelf thrice a day, and prays ſeven hours on his knees, lyes upon the bare grounds, ſerves the ſick, and diſtributes part of his Alms to other poor people. And all this to tame his fleſh, and get the maſtery over ſelf-love, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf the better for his devout Pilgrimage into the Holy Land. This hardſhip and auſterity of his, go with the Dr. for an argument of <hi>Fanaticiſm;</hi> for it is probable he may be of their opinion, who deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe St. <hi>John</hi> in the Deſert, leading a good commodious kind of life, <hi>[Vide Cern. a lap. in Matt.</hi> 3. 4.] wearing watered Chamlet, feeding on Lobſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But we muſt help him to reconcile St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with his faſting, for he cannot underſtand why he begg'd every day, and yet faſted ſix days in the week. Let him therefore look bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his Authors, and he will find, that he faſted onely with bread and water, and begg'd that, and diſtributed the reſt of his Alms unto other poor Creatures. One thing more is here worth your obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Doctor in his whole Narration, ſays not one word of his giving away his Mule, and travelling on Foot, becauſe you know a <hi>Knight Errant,</hi> is no body without his <hi>Roſonante.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. In this retirement and pennance at <hi>Manreſa,</hi> St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was not only, grievouſly vext with ſcruples about his Confeſſions (a diſeaſe which Proteſtants are not much troubled with) but alſo furiouſly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted by divers temptations; all which he manfully overcame, by the particular aſſiſtance of Gods grace, and by following the conduct of his Confeſſor. One among the reſt was, to throw himſelf out of a Window: and this the Doctor only mentions out of <hi>Maffejus, [Maff. c.</hi> 6. <hi>Ribad. c.</hi> 6.] but alſo abuſes him as well as the Saint, making him ſay, that he was <hi>near</hi> doing it; when he only ſays, he was tempted to do it; as our Bleſſed Saviour was to throw himſelf down from the Pinnacle of the Temple. And <hi>Ribadeneira</hi> expreſly notes, theſe devout aſpirations which he uſed, to reſiſt that temptation: <hi>Lord I will not do it. I will not offend thee, for thou art my God, my ſtrength; why haſt thou forſaken me? and why go I ſorrowful while the enemy afflicts me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. It pleaſed God after theſe ſharp tryals of his ſervant, not onely to reſtore him to a great peace and quiet of mind, but to favour him with many extraordinary viſions and revelations. In one of his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, while he was devoutly reciting our Bleſſed Lady's Office, he had
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62701:11"/> a clear ſight given him of the bleſſed Trinity, under a corporeal repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation. At other times upon a ſudden, ſuch clear Lights were infus'd into his Soul, that without the help of any Maſter he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood many things, not only of the Creation of the World, and other Myſteries of our Faith, but of ſubtle Speculations, belonging to the hidden Secrets of Nature, as perfectly, as if they had been repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him in a clear Chriſtal Glaſs; ſo that he learnt more in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, by this infuſed knowledge, then he could have got by long Study. In one of his Extaſies, he continued eight dayes, without any other ſign of life, but a ſoft beating of his Heart, and when he came to himſelf, as out of a ſweet ſlumber, he opened his Eyes and repeated the name of Jeſus, and immediately roſe up, to the aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of many that were preſent; of whom we have it, ſays <hi>Riba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneica,</hi> for St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was not the man, that ever ſpoke of it in all his Life. In this Extaſy ſays <hi>Orlandinus</hi> it is credibly believed, that as the Apoſtle in his three days rapture to the third Heaven, probably ſaw the whole form and myſterious order of Gods Church; ſo <hi>Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> had a ſight given him of the whole Form and Model of the Society, which he was to found. Theſe extraordinary favours of God, have no more credit with the Doctor, then if they were ſo many, old Wives tales. But let him give Ear to that of the Apoſtle; <hi>The ſenſual man perceives not thoſe things which are of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14.</note> 
               <hi>the Spirit of God; for it is fooliſhneſs to him, and he cannot underſtand,</hi> &amp;c. he muſt give others leave to believe, there was ſomething more then ordinary in theſe occaſions; for had he not got an infuſed knowledge, by thoſe Divine viſits how could he (ignorant as he was in all humane Sciences) have compos'd a large Treatiſe of the bleſſed Trinity, or diſcourſe of that myſtery, as he did to the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of all thoſe that heard him, or how could he have written, ſuch an excellent Book as that of the ſpiritual Exerciſes? in which (to ſay nothing of other pions Inſtructions) he teaches, with a ſingular dexterity and method, divers wayes of Prayer and Contemplation, fit for the reformation of manners and progreſs in all vertue; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes admirable Rules for the examination of our conſciences, rooting out our vicious habits, bridling our immortified Paſſions, diſcerning Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, overcoming Scruples, and chuſing a ſtate of life according to Gods will. A Book which has drawn infinite Souls, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Secular; from a looſe kind Converſation, to a ſtrict penitential Life. A Book which is of that general eſteem in the Church, that it has been approved by his Holineſs, <hi>Paulus</hi> 3 <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1548. without
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62701:12"/> altering the leaſt tittle, and recommended as a work of great Piety, and very uſeful for the benefit of Souls, and acknowledg'd by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals of the holy Rites, to have proceeded from ſupernatural light and illuſtration; and not from the Art and Invention of man. But ſince I am upon this Theme, you may expect that I take notice, of a notorious falſe aſperſion, which the Dr. <hi>[pag.</hi> 341.] in another place of his Book, has caſt upon this moſt excellent work; as if the Saint had taught there, I know not what fond Doctrine, about private Revelations. The place, he confeſſes, is not in the Editions that are now extant; ſo that we have this at leaſt, that the Jeſuits do not own the Doctrine, but he takes it upon the ſole warrant of a libellous Author, <hi>[Mor. Pract. of the Ieſuits p.</hi> 379] who pretends to have it out of an old Edition, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1574. I ſay libellous Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, for his Book was publickly burnt in <hi>Paris</hi> by the common Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, by the <hi>French</hi> Kings expreſs order, and I pray take notice of this, as often as you ſhall meet with the ſame Author. The folly of this ſlander appears by this, that the Copies we have, are found con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Original, which was approv'd by his Holineſs, word for word, and which the Jeſuits had no reaſon to corrupt, by foiſting in ſuch a piece of Nonſenſe, as he imagines; and ſoon after for meer ſhame, to ſteal it out of all the Copies. There is much more cauſe to think (if there ever were ſuch an Edition) that it was put out by no Friends of the Jeſuits. But I muſt not forget one of the Doctors Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, which (though intended as a jeer) makes not a little for the honour of the Saint. Having told us, what I lately obſerv'd out of <hi>Orlandinus,</hi> that ſome think it probable, that he ſaw the frame and model of the Society in his eight days extaſy, he cries out <hi>a bleſſed ſight! if he ſaw all the conſequences of it too.</hi> I am clearly of his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in this point: it was <hi>a bleſſed ſight,</hi> to ſee his order ſo ſtrangely increas'd and diſpers'd all over the habitable World, whereas <hi>Luther</hi> and other modern Sectaries, could never get footing beyond the <hi>Alps</hi> or <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Mountains. It was <hi>a bleſſed ſight,</hi> to ſee how conſtantly his Children laboured for the good of Souls, and how readily they ſhed their Blood for the true Faith; what a world of good was to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, by his ſetting up Schools every where, for the Education of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Piety and Learning; what a wonderful reformation was to enſue in all <hi>Europe,</hi> and what miraculous Converſions, were to be wrought by his Followers, all over the new World: in <hi>America Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa.</hi> This I ſay was a moſt <hi>bleſſed ſight,</hi> to ſee ſo many Souls, brought to the Faith of Chriſt, by thoſe of his order, in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62701:12"/> 
               <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> in <hi>Iaponia, Braſil, Aethiopio, China, &amp;c.</hi> For <hi>Boeſius <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>de ſignis Eccl. l.</hi> 6. ſticks not to challenge all Sectaries, from <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> their grand Patriark, and Ringleader, to theſe preſent dayes, to produce but as many ſouls drawn to their Factions, as were converted from Paganiſme to the Chriſtian ſaith, by S. <hi>Xaverius</hi> alone, the number, ſaies he, amounting to ten hundred thouſand. I know the Dr. will be ready heer to repeat that fond ſtory, which he has ſet down, <hi>pa.</hi> 439. of the Jeſuits way of converting the Pagans in <hi>China;</hi> but till I meet it there, let it ſuffice to tell you, the Author he leans upon, is a Libelling Janſeniſt.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Give me leave Sir, to pauſe here a while, and make a ſhort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, upon what has been already deliver'd, concerning S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his life. You have ſeen his converſton, and rigorous pennance, and ſome of his divine illuſtrations and viſions, but perhaps you do not ſee, how illogically the Doctor goes to work, to conclude him to be a Fanatick, out of all this. Reduce but his diſcourſes into Syllogiſms, and this will clearly appear. For example thus. <hi>Whoſoever upon reading the lives of Chriſt and his Saints, leaves the world to conſecrate himſelf intirely to Gods ſervice is a Fanatick,</hi> can you deny this? <hi>but</hi> S. <hi>Ignatius did ſo,</hi> as the Dr. grants, <hi>ergo he was a Fanatick,</hi> a wonderful piece of Logick. Again, <hi>Whoſoever voluntarily embraces poverty, and gives himſelf to much Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Faſting, and corporal auſterities is a Fanatick</hi> (as well as St. <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist) but</hi> S. <hi>Ignatius did ſo,</hi> ergo, <hi>he was a Phanatick.</hi> Yet again, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever watches and Prayes all night in the Church, as pious Knights were wont to do in old times, before their Inſtalment, is a Fanatick.</hi> For no body muſt do that for Gods ſake, which others do for ceremony) <hi>ergo he was a Phanatick.</hi> Yet once more, <hi>Whoſoever has Revelations and viſions is a Phanatick</hi> (For many Saints have had them as you ſhall ſee towards the end of my letter) <hi>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>go he was a Phanatick.</hi> Let us proceed.</p>
            <p n="17">17. It ſeems S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> did not ſo ingroſs all viſions to himſelf, but others had ſome too: for at <hi>Barcellona</hi> in his way to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> the Lady <hi>Elizabeth Roſella</hi> ſaw a great ſhining light about his head, whilſt he was humbly ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting amongſt the boyes at a Sermon in the Church, and heard a voice within her, which bid her call him and treat him like a Saint. There was a Senator alſo at <hi>Venice,</hi> had a like viſion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, checking him for lying at his eaſe, while the ſervant of God <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> lay in the Streets, at which voice he ſuddainly roſe up, found him &amp; brought him into his houſe, and treated him civilly, though the Saint next day made choice of a worſe lodging. Beſides one <hi>Iohn Paſchal,</hi> often ſaw him elevated in the air, ſome cubits above ground. Perhaps
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62701:13"/> theſe are the viſions, which muſt prove him a <hi>Fanatick.</hi> If ſo, he muſt argue thus. <hi>The Lady</hi> Elizabeth Roſella, <hi>the Venetian Senator, and Paſchalis, had their viſions in relation to his ſanctity of life,</hi> ergo <hi>he was a Fanatick.</hi> But where will he have a minor to make up the Sillogiſme in right forme? for ſay they were illuded, at moſt it will prove <hi>them Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks,</hi> but not <hi>him.</hi> That indeed of <hi>Roſella</hi> ſeems ſomething ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, as he relates it, for he makes her to have ſeen <hi>a great ſhining about his mouth,</hi> but in this I muſt once more appeal to the Lads of <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> School, whether <hi>os oris</hi> in good Latin do not often ſignify the whole countenance, and whether they would offer to tranſlate: <hi>Os humeroſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Deo ſimilis,</hi> like a God in mouth and Shoulders, or <hi>Os homini ſublime dedit,</hi> Nature has given man a ſublime mouth. At leaſt <hi>Ribado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neira</hi> one of his Authors has <hi>caput</hi> inſtead of <hi>os,</hi> and that I am ſure he will not Engliſh <hi>mouth</hi> leaſt the Boys laugh more at him.</p>
            <p n="18">18. S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was a well bred Gavalier, and a great Courtier in his time, (as I told you before) and had affected ceremonies and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, according to the mode, but after his Converſion, one of his chief cares was, how to expiate this vanity of too much courtſhip. The way he took was, to conceal his birth and education, ſo as to be taken for a contemptible perſon. This made him lay aſide the Gentleman, and carry himſelf in all company, as if he had been born and bred a meer clown, calling every body by his name, without any Titles of honour or reſpect. Now in his return from <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> (in which voyage there are many devout paſſages and many clear tokens of Gods providence to the Saint) which the Dr. was pleaſed to omit) as he was paſſing through <hi>Italy,</hi> he was taken for a ſpy, by the Spaniſh Souldiers, and in a ſcornful and rude manner, drag'd along the ſtreets, and carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before their Commander. In this occaſion he bethought himſelf, whether it were not more diſcretion, to alter his carriage, and demean himſelf with more civility the better to get off; but finding this to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a baſe and ſervile kind of fear, he reſolves not to change his ſtyle, and therefore neither puts off his hat, nor ſcarce ſpeaks for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but remains for the moſt part ſilent, that he might be taken for a fool or a madman. And he miſt not his aim, for it was upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that the Captain diſmiſt him, and the Souldiers abuſed him ſhamefully, only one of them had the compaſſion and kindneſs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain him and protect him, till he got out of their reach. However the Dr. is of opinion, <hi>he might have ſav'd himſelf the labour of whipping himſelf that day the ſouldiers doing him that office very effectually.</hi> But for all the Doctors flouts and jeers, the Saint, who had a true value and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62701:13"/> eſtimate of the chriſtian vertues of patience and humility, knew how to make good uſe of ſuch ſufferings. Nor did he ever after change his opinion, as to this point, but was often heard ſay, that were it not for loſing his authority (which is neceſſary to do good with our neighbour) he would moſt willingly walk the ſtreets in a contemptible manner, all ſtuck with feathers, and half naked, to be hooted at by the boyes, and taken for a mad man. Nor did he keep this humble ſpirit to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf but ſtrove to communicate it unto all his children in that truly E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical conſtitution, which he preſcribes for all his to follow, and runs thus, <hi>[Sum. Conſt.</hi> §. 11. <hi>They muſt diligently obſerve, eſteeming it a matter of great value and main importance in the ſight of our Creator and Lord, how greatly it helps and makes for the profit of a ſpiritual life, to abhorr wholly and not in part, all things which the world loves and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, and to admit and deſire to their uttermost power, whatſoever Chriſt our Lord loved and embraced. For as worldly men do follow Love, and ſeek with great diligence, thoſe things which are of the world, to Wit, honours, Fame and the opinion of a great name upon earth, as the world teaches them: ſo thoſe that go forward in ſpirit, and ſeriouſly follow Chriſt our Lord, do love and fervently deſire ſuch things as are altogether contrary: that is, they covet to be cloathed with the ſame garment and Livery with our Lord, for his love and reverence; in ſo much, as if it might be without any offence of the Divine Majesty, and without ſin of their neighbour, they would be content to ſuffer reproaches, ſlanders, injuries<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to be held and accounted fooles (yet without any occaſion given by them) becauſe they earneſtly deſire to reſemble and imitate in ſome ſort their Creator and Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and to be cloathed with his garments, and livery ſince he cloathed himſelf with the ſame, for our greater good and ſpiritual profit, and gave us example<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that in all things, as far as by the aſſiſtance of Gods grace we may, we ſhould imitate and follow him; ſeeing he is the true way, that leads men to life.</hi> Thus he, and the next conſtitution is to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>To the end this degree of perfection ſo pretious in a ſpiritual life, may be the better attained; let it be every one's chiefeſt and greateſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, to ſeek in our Lord his own greater abnegation, and continual mortification, as much as he can, in all things</hi> This is a language to which the Doctor ſeems a great ſtranger, and he may ſee by it, that he deales with patient adverſaries, who otherwiſe would have paid him in his own coyn long before this. But I muſt not think to eſcape ſo; from S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his carriage to the Captain, the Doctor will needs have it, that he was <hi>the firſt founder of that Fanatick ſect which is diſtinguiſht ſo much from others by denying common civilities to men.</hi> By his favour, the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62701:14"/> bare denying civilities, make not a <hi>Fanatick;</hi> otherwiſe every Clown that knows not how to put off his Hat, or make a Leg or that perſonates a <hi>Fanatick</hi> upon the Stage, muſt of neceſſity be a <hi>Fanatick.</hi> There is ſomething more then goes to the making it a diſtinctive ſign of a <hi>Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick;</hi> and that is to do it out of a ſettled judgement, that there is no diſtinction of Perſons to be made, nor any more reſpect due to one than to another: Now it is a clear Caſe that St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was not of this <hi>Fanatical</hi> perſwaſion, but onely had a mind to humble himſelf, and be taken for a Fool, or an ignorant Clown, the more to reſemble his Maſter when he was before <hi>Herod.</hi> And this alſo in the heat of his firſt fervour, when all Maſters of Spirit, allow Saints, ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their ordinary ſtrain of other men: For otherwiſe it is well known, that when St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was once engaged in an Apoſtolical cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, no man could be more civil and complaiſant, in a Religious way than he: in ſo much that the Doctor ſoon after, takes notice of his winning way, and obliging carriage, which he calls <hi>obſequiouſneſs, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> and <hi>inſinuation;</hi> ſo that if he had before put on the diſguiſe of a <hi>Quaker,</hi> it ſeems he ſoon put it off. What the Doctor has to reply I know not, but in the way of arguing I doubt he would have much ado to excuſe our bleſſed Lord's carriage before <hi>Herod</hi> from countenancing <hi>Fanaticiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. Being returned to <hi>Barcellona,</hi> to make himſelf a fitter Inſtrument to do good with his Neighbour; at three and thirty years of age, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies himſelf to learn Grammar Rules, and with all returns to his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted task of rigorous pennance, which in his travailing for healths ſake, he had thought ſit to moderate. And his love of ſuffering found out a new invention, to corzen the World, and go bare foot without the leaſt ſign of oſtentation; for by little and little, he had ſo pared away the ſoles of his Shooes, that he trod upon the bare ground, though his Feet were covered with the upper Leathers. At his ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, he was ſo carried with ſenſible ſeelings, and tenderneſs of devotion that he could attend to nothing elſe. The word <hi>Amo</hi> was ſufficient, to put him upon Acts of divine Love, and tranſport him out of himſelf. This amaz'd him, and the rather becauſe he had not the ſame feelings of Devotion, when he had moſt reaſon to expect them, as when he ſetled himſelf to Prayer, or diſpoſ'd himſelf to receive the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Whence he concludes it to be an illuſion of the Enemy, and to confound and vanquiſh him the better, he humbly caſts himſelf at his Maſters feet, and beſeeches him to be as rigorous in dayly exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Leſſons of him, as he was to the Boys, and as ſevere in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62701:14"/> him, when he could not ſay them. After which Act of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he grew to be ſo good a Proficient, that in two years times, he was judg'd fit, to go to his higher Courſes. Wherefore he goes to <hi>Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> and in that Univerſity privately ſtudies <hi>Logick, Phyſicks</hi> and <hi>Divinity</hi> all together, by the perſwaſion of ſome of his Friends, who by reaſon of his Age, thought it better for him to make a ſhort courſe: But undertaking too much at once, it was not like to ſucceed. And beſides he wanted not other employments to diſtract him; for he continued his begging from Door to Door, and omitted no occaſion of drawing his Neighbour unto Gods ſervice by pious Diſcourſes, which the Doctor will needs call Sermons, becauſe in Latine it is <hi>Sermones,</hi> at <hi>Eaton School,</hi> a Boy would be called to the Ferula for conſtruing ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Now becauſe many were thus ſuddenly drawn by him to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter courſe of Life, it bred a great noiſe in the Town, and ſtrict inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition was made into his manner of Life and Doctrine by <hi>Figueroa</hi> the Vicar-general of <hi>Toledo,</hi> that the truth might appear better, he was apprehended, and kept in Priſon one and fourty dayes: After which the Vicar declared, that nothing could be found worthy of reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either in his Life or Doctrine, onely he wiſht him to wear the ſame habit with other Students, and not to handle points of Divinity, till he had ſtudied it four years. Soon after this, with advice of the Arch-biſhop he removes to <hi>Salamanca,</hi> but there falls into the ſame troubles he had met with at <hi>Alcala;</hi> for his Zeal ſtill carrying him on to ſtir up the Peoples hearts to a holy love and fear of our Lord, he was queſtion'd by the <hi>Sub-Prior</hi> of the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> why he took upon him to Preach without Learning; <hi>Ignatius</hi> anſwered, he did not Preach, but make familiar Diſcourſes concerning Vice and Vertue, to bring the People to the hatred of one, and love of the other. (This the Doctor expreſſes ridiculouſly by the Phanatick Phraſe of <hi>holding forth)</hi> the <hi>Sub-Prior</hi> reply'd; this was not to be done by unlearn'd Perſons (he did no ſay this was Preaching as the Doctor tranſlates it) unleſs he pretended to do it by divine Inſpiration. For that ſayes St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> I will give an account of my ſelf, when I am juridically exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd. This bred a farther ſuſpition in a dangerous time; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by order of the Vicar, he and ſome of his Companions were clapt up in Priſon. But in that very place he continued to ſpeak freely, in the commendation of Vertue, and reprehenſion of Vice, and to draw his Auditors from the vain love of the World, and there was a great flocking to hear him, and he found much comfort to ſee himſelf in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62701:15"/> Chains without fault, telling thoſe that came to condole with him, that they little knew the ſweetneſs, which lies in the Croſs of Chriſt, (ſo do the Quakers ſays the Doctor) and ſo did the holy Martyrs in the Primitive Church ſay I. After 21 dayes he was call'd before the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car, where ſayes the Doctor he <hi>Preached</hi> at large upon ſeveral points of Divinity, under pretenſe of anſwering Queſtions. But had he followed his Authors, as he Profeſſes, he ſhould have ſaid, he gave ſo good an account of divers ſubtle Queſtions of Religion, and out of the Canon Law, and being bid to diſcourſe upon the firſt Commad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the ſame manner, as if he were before the People, he did it with ſo much wiſdom and gravity, that the Vicar and all that heard him were aſtoniſhed. Whereupon he and his Companions were declared men of a pure and ſincere life, and ſo honourably diſmiſt. Onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Vicar, had ſeen certain Rules, which St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> gives in his ſpiritual Exerciſes, how to diſtinguiſh thoughts, when they are venial Sins, and when mortal; he was charged not to meddle with ſuch nice points, till he had ſtudied his Divinity. This the Saint did not a little reſent, that he ſhould be thus reſtrained from making uſe of thoſe Rules, which the Vicar himſelf had allowed to be ſolid and good. One thing which concurr'd to prove them innocent, was, that having a fair occaſion to make their eſcape out of Priſon, as the other Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners had done, by the negligence of their Keeper, they alone would not ſtir.</p>
            <p n="21">21. After all theſe vexations (which were of no advantage to his ſtudies) away he goes for <hi>Paris</hi> (to ſee ſaies the Dr. whether he could have any better luck there) and well might he fly ſuch perſecutions, as the great <hi>Athanaſius</hi> did, eſpecially upon the warrant of his Captain <hi>Chriſt Ieſus: when they ſhall perſecute you in this City fly into another.</hi> Matt. 10. 23 But he had a farther aim in it (ſaies <hi>Orlandinus)</hi> Orlan. n. 63. to put himſelf upon a neceſſity, of dealing leſs with his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for want of the French Language, and ſo to fall cloſer to his book, which he reſolves now to follow in good earneſt, and for a time to lay aſide part of his rigorous pennance, which could not well ſtand with the labour of ſtudying. And becauſe experience had taught him, that he had made more haſt then good ſpeed; to lay a good Foundation of the Latine Tongue, he falls again to repeat his Grammar, (a ſad Caſe cries the Doctor, that alter ſo much Schooling, and ſo many Revelations, he ſhould be yet ſo great a Dunce, as not to know his Grammar.) I let the jeer paſs, which I am ſure the Saint would have heard with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. Yet let me tell the Doctor, St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> would have then
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62701:15"/> conſtrued <hi>literae; os; ſermones, baculus ternatilis, calceus ex ſparto, patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> &amp;c. more properly than <hi>He</hi> has done after all his <hi>Schooling.</hi> After 18 moneths ſpent in humanity he heard his Philoſophy, and took the degree of Maſter of Arts, and then ſtudied Divinity, where ſaies the Doctor <hi>(he got juſt enough, to keep him from being an Heretick, for ſo much Maffejus his words imply)</hi> where Orlandinus n. 72. Witneſſeſs that one of the prime Doctors of that faculty, would have had him commence Doctor of Divinity, before he had paſſed <hi>Maſter</hi> of <hi>Arts,</hi> profeſſing that he knew not how to own himſelf a <hi>Doctor,</hi> while <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> who had taught him ſo much, had not that title. And <hi>Maffejus</hi> his words imply, that he got as much as to give a good account of his Faith and Doctrine according to the ſenſe of the holy Fathers, without any ſuſpition of novelty. A degree of Learning which the Doctor is not yet arrived to, for all he ſlights it ſo much.</p>
            <p n="22">22. He has here another ſlurt at his poverty, which forced him to make ſeveral excurſions to beg neceſſaries for his ſubſiſtence, but he ſaies nothing of his going over into <hi>England,</hi> becauſe perhaps he was there treated, with more civility then he thinks he deſerved. While he was at <hi>Antwerp</hi> (upon a like occaſion) he told one <hi>Quadratus</hi> a Spaniſh Merchant, that he was one day to be the Founder of a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Society in <hi>Spain,</hi> which many years after really ſell out, though at that time there was little probability of any ſuch thing: A good Argument that he had the Spirit of Prophecy to foretell it, for all the Doctors Parentheſes and Jeers to the contrary. And I could give him many other inſtances of his Prophetical Spirit, which cannot be denied: as his foretelling <hi>Francis Borgia</hi> whilſt he was yet Duke of <hi>Gandia,</hi> and Father <hi>Iames Laynes,</hi> that they ſhould be Generals of the Society of Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="23">23. All did not go ſo ſmooth with him at <hi>Paris,</hi> but he met with his troubles there as well as he had done in <hi>Spain:</hi> For having with his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed zeal drawn ſome Students of the Colledge of St. <hi>Barbara,</hi> where he ſtudied to a perfecter courſe of life; ſo as to live upon alms, frequent the Sacraments, and beſtow more time in Prayer upon Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val dayes; and one among the reſt by his perſwaſions, as they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, having not only left the Colledge, but the World too, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt naked upon the Croſs; there was a great ſtir about it and ſuch a general Animoſity rais'd againſt him, that they were ready to give him publick correction. For the Colledge Gates were ſhut, and the Bell and rung to call all the Collegians together, when the Saint was ſo far from declining, that ſhameful puniſhment, that he went to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62701:16"/> Rector, and with much generoſity and freedom told him, that for his part he was both ready and willing to undergo the correction, but that he might do well to conſider whether Gods Cauſe would not alſo ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer by it, if it were reported that he had ſuffer'd onely for drawing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ers to more piety; which wrought ſo with the Rector, that before all the Maſters and Scholars he caſt himſelf at his Feet, and with tears in his Eyes askt him pardon as of a Saint; <hi>[Orland. n.</hi> 71. <hi>Ribad. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. who made little reckoning of his own ſufferings, provided they might ſtand with Gods greater glory and the good of Souls; and it is worth the obſerving, that this Rector ever after retain'd ſuch an affection to him, and to all his Children for his ſake, that he was the prime Perſon that perſwaded <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> to ſend the Fathers of the Society into the <hi>Indies: [Ribad ibid. c.</hi> 16. where they have ſince done ſuch wonders in the Converſion of Souls. Here the Dr. wants not his Jeers; but what uſe he can make of this paſſage to prove St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> a <hi>Fanatick,</hi> paſſes my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing let him put his Argument in form, and it will be as good as thoſe I made for him.</p>
            <p n="24">24. He runs on after the ſame rate, and makes a ſlight of two moſt incomparable Examples of St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity. <hi>I omit,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>his flying or rather being carried as it were in a rapture from</hi> Paris <hi>to</hi> Roven, <hi>and the joy and extatick expreſſion he had in it; his ſtanding up in Dirt and Mire to the Neck to repreſent to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, the filthineſs of the ſin. he liv'd in.</hi> Had he meant fairly and honeſtly, he would never have thus ſlubbard over two ſuch rare paſſages hardly to be parellel'd in the Lives of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Saints. For the firſt then you are to know, that one of St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Fellow Students at <hi>Paris</hi> had cheated him of a good Alms, which was ſent him out of <hi>Spain</hi> to help him to pay for his board, and which out of confidence he had truſted in his hands; ſo that being thus diſappointed of the money, he was forc'd to retire to the Hoſpital and beg again for his living. Now this ungrateful Wretch, having ſpent the money, and afterwards falling ſick at <hi>Roven</hi> in his way to <hi>Spain,</hi> writ earneſtly to St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> to beſeech him for Charity ſake to have compaſſion on him, and take ſome order for his neceſſary relief, Upon the receipt of which Letter, <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> immediately goes for <hi>Roven</hi> or rather flies thither upon the Wings of Love, for ſure it muſt have been ſome divine Rapture, that could carry him in three dayes 28 Leagues bare Foot as he was, and without Eating or Drinking at all by the way; for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62701:16"/> ſo he perform'd the journey with a wonderful alacrity, offering up all that labour and pennance for the health of a Perſon, that had play'd him ſuch an unworthy trick. And Almighty God was ſo well pleas'd with his Charity, and gave ſuch a bleſſing to his endeavours, that the man was not ſoon only reſtor'd to his health, but alſo by his mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht with conveniences to purſue his intended Journey. The ſecond was in this manner: he had often labour'd in vain to reclaim a Freind of his (the charitable Dr. would have you think it was one of <hi>his companions)</hi> from his diſhoneſt courſe of Life, and knowing which way he was to paſs to his Miſtreſs, he caſt himſelf naked up to the Neck into a freezing Lake (not Dirt and Mire as the Dr. has it) and there cried out to him as he ſaw him paſs: <hi>Whether goeſt thou miſerable Wretch? do'ſt thou not ſee the Sword of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Iuſtice hanging over thy head? go then and ſatisfie thy Luſt, I'le here ſtrive by my ſuffering to quench thy Helliſh Flames, and divert Gods Vengeance from pouring down upon thee.</hi> This Heroical Act of fraternal Charity, this painful remedy to preſerve ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Chaſtity (which we admire in Saints even when it was their own Caſe) ſtruck his Freind with ſuch aſtoniſhment and horror, that he ſuddainly broke off all the Chains of his diſhoneſt affections, and ſettled himſef to a chaſt Life.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Now you are to take notice, ſaies the Doctor, that his deſign being to form a Society, he had for that purpoſe us'd himſelf to all the Acts of Inſinuation imaginable, accomodating himſelf to the humours of the Perſons he had to do with, endeavouring to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige all men, with expreſſions of their greateſt kindneſs, bearing all the affronts with wonderful diſſimulation (I'll warrant you he put off his Hat too, and us'd other common civilities) what harm in all this? does it ſhew a <hi>Fanatical</hi> or an <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Spirit <hi>to become all things to all men, that he might ſave all?</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 22. By theſe Acts he labours, ſaies he, to get ſome of the moſt hopeful Students in the Univerſity to him, and at laſt prevails upon nine, to joyn with him: He ſtudies their humours, and applies himſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, not acquainting them at firſt with his deſign, but by degrees prepares them for it. Amongſt them <hi>Xaverius</hi> at firſt laugh'd at him, but was won by his patience, (not <hi>Flattery,</hi> as the Doctor conſtrues <hi>Patientia)</hi> and obſequiouſneſs. Having now got Perſons to his mind, he opens his intentions to them, and they all conclude, to meet privately at <hi>Mont martyr</hi> a mile out of <hi>Paris:</hi> here they all vow'd before the bleſſed Sacrament, from that inſtant to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62701:17"/> leave the World, and live in perpetual chaſtity, never to receive any thing for their Maſſes by way of recompence, to renounce all propriety at the end of their ſtudies, and then (all other reſpects laid aſide) to go in Pilgrimage, to viſit the holy Places at <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> But if that Journey could not be compaſſed within a year, then to repair to his Holineſs, and offer him their beſt ſervice, for the Spiritual good of their Neighbour. This happened (for the firſt time) <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1534. upon the Aſſumption of our bleſſed Lady, to whoſe holy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, they particularly commended themſelves. After this <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> very prudently uſed all means, to keep them all united together in perfect charity, and for fear leaſt ſome of their Freinds in <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhould take them off from theſe good intentions, he freely offers to go him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to diſpatch their buſineſs. All this while do you perceive where the <hi>Fanaticiſme</hi> lies?</p>
            <p n="26">26. In <hi>Spain</hi> he was followed by ſuch a multitude of People, that he was fain to Preach in the Fields, and though his Voice were but weak, yet he was heard diſtinctly above a quarter of a mile. The Doctor takes this to be a Fable, though <hi>Orlandinus</hi> relate it as a thing atteſted by many Perſons then preſent. <hi>Maffejus</hi> is more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to him, for without intreaty he believes what he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it of the Horſe, which carried S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> into <hi>Spain:</hi> how having left him to the Hoſpital, they would never after make uſe of him, but preſerv'd him in good liking all his Life time. This he makes merry with, as if the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had done it out of reverence to the Beaſt, as being a <hi>conſecrated Horſe:</hi> But his Author ſaies expreſly that they did it <hi>in Ignatii memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am:</hi> that is for <hi>Ignatius</hi> his ſake; in which I ſee no great myſtery. Yet if it muſt be a piece of <hi>Fanaticiſme,</hi> let the People of the Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital look to it.</p>
            <p n="27">27. His next Journey was for <hi>Venice,</hi> where his Companions were to meet him by agreement, to embark for <hi>Paleſtin,</hi> but finding that Voyage obſtructed by the War, which was broken out, between the <hi>Turk</hi> and the <hi>Venetians</hi> (their courage being coold, ſaies the Dr.) they diſperſt themſelves up and down the Country (wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, ſaies he, as if they had been Gypſies) and exercis'd their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Functions of Preaching, ſometimes in the very Streets, where they could get People together, a thing not ſo unuſual as the Dr. apprehends, but practis'd this very day in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf. And though they ſpoke but imperfect <hi>Italian,</hi> yet they converted many, as their Followers have done, ſaies the Doctor, from the uſe of Laces and Ribbands. What a piece of impertinency have we here?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62701:17"/> the World knows how many millions of Souls, have by their zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Preaching, been drawn to the Faith of Chriſt, from Paganiſme and Hereſie, and from a wicked Life, and all this the Dr. calls leaving the uſe of Laces and Ribbands. But did not the Lady's alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times leave his Church; I'le be bound if he would not write ſuch bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Invectives and biting Satyrs againſt the Jeſuits and other Religious, as he does. Who would think he ſhould find any thing to carp at, in St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> and his Companions pious cuſtome, of joyning toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Prayer, in all matters of debate, and following that opinion the moſt were off<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> after their Pray'r: Yet by chopping in <hi>ſeeking God</hi> inſtead of <hi>Praying</hi> he would have his Reader believe they were all turn'd <hi>Seekers.</hi> In this ſenſe I confeſs they were <hi>Seekers</hi> that they ſought nothing but Gods greater glory in all things, as St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> had taught them, whoſe proper <hi>deviſe</hi> was; <hi>Ad majorem Dei gloriam, to Gods greater glory,</hi> which he fixt upon all his actions, to inflame himſelf, to do yet more and more for Gods honour and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p n="28">28. Now becauſe the Authors of his Life take notice, that his Viſions and Revelations, which were nothing ſo frequent in time of his ſtudies, as they had been at <hi>Manreſa,</hi> began to be as frequent as ever; He moſt malitiouſly attributes it to the hope he had of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a confirmation of his Order, as if he had had them at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as well as <hi>Mahomet;</hi> or in plain Engliſh, as if he had play'd the cheat and onely pretended to receive ſuch favours from Heaven, which he forg'd to bring about his ends. He only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions two of theſe Viſions. The firſt was in his way to <hi>Rome;</hi> where entring into a Church to pray, he was rapt into an Extaſie, and ſaw God the Father commending him and his Companions, to the favour of his bleſſed Son, who alſo appeared at the ſame time with his Croſs upon his Shoulders, and ſpake unto him theſe comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table words: <hi>I will be favourable to you at</hi> Rome. Which was the chief Cauſe, that in the confirmation of his Order, it was call'd the <hi>Society of Ieſus.</hi> The other was at <hi>Monte Caſſino,</hi> where he ſaw the Soul of <hi>Hoſius,</hi> one his of Companions lately dead, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Heaven; and a little after amongſt many other glorious Saints.</p>
            <p n="29">29. Notwithſtanding all this, ſaies the Dr. they met with great difficulties at <hi>Rome.</hi> It is very true they did: but he does not tell us how they came off, by the favourable aſſiſtance, which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62701:18"/> our B. Saviour had promiſed them. The ſtory is to be ſeen at large in <hi>Orlandinus</hi> and <hi>Ribadeneira. Orlan. l.</hi> 2. <hi>n. c.</hi> 47. <hi>Ribal. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 14. The ſhort of it is this. One <hi>Auſtin</hi> of <hi>Piedmont</hi> an <hi>Auſtin</hi> Fryer by profeſſion, but a conceald <hi>Lutheran,</hi> had been blam'd by the Fathers for preaching falſe doctrine. He conſpires with one <hi>Michael;</hi> and this wicked fellow gives out, that <hi>Ignatius</hi> had been condemned for an Heretick, firſt in <hi>Spain</hi> then at <hi>Paris,</hi> and laſtly at <hi>Venice.</hi> This upon examination was found to be a meer ſlander, and <hi>Michael</hi> was ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to baniſhment, and S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> and his companions, were by a publick ſentence (which is to be ſeen in the Authors) juridically declar'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent perſons. And that you may ſee what a hand Gods providence had in their defence, and that he had not forgot his promiſe to S. <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> of being <hi>favourable to him at Rome;</hi> in the very ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k of time, that they lay under this cloud of Perſecution, <hi>Figueroa</hi> the Vicar ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of <hi>Toledo,</hi> who upon a like ſlaunder at <hi>Alcala<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> had caſt <hi>Ignatius</hi> into Priſon, and ſound him innocent, comes to <hi>Rome,</hi> and the other two alſo, who had been his Judges at <hi>Paris,</hi> and <hi>Venice;</hi> and all theſe gave teſtimony of his innocen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y beyond all exception. And not long after this, <hi>Auſtin</hi> of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> who was the chief projector in framing the falſe accuſation, publickly profeſſed himſelf a <hi>Lutheran,</hi> and the reſt of his inſtruments grew to be of ſuch wicked lives, that one was burnt in <hi>effigie</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and another was condemn'd to perpetual im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, though he afterwards repented, and was aſſiſted at his death by one of the Fathers. 30, Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the 3. being throughly ſatisfyed of their being ſerviceable to the Church (ſaies the Dr. ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y truly which is a wonder) the Order was confirmed 3<hi>d. Octob. An. D.</hi> 1540. And the Pope himſelf ſaies he, became <hi>enthuſiaſtical</hi> too, for having read the <hi>Formula</hi> of the inſtitute of the Society, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the firſt draught of the rule penn'd by S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> he cryed out <hi>The ſpirit of God is here.</hi> One of the Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dinals had oppos'd himſelf at firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but was ſoon gained by the Saints pennance and prayers, and three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Maſſes, which he and his friends offerd up for that intention, and ſuddainly chang'd his mind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; publickly profeſſed; that although it was a thing much againſt his dictamen, to multiply religious orders, yet as to the inſtitute of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> he neither durſt nor could oppoſe it. I would gladly here omit the Drs. prophane jeſt upon the Maſſes and Prayers, that were offer'd, and not ſully my Paper with it; <hi>that it muſt be a hard heart indeed that would not yeild with ſo much ſuppling.</hi> Where you ſee he is not content to jeer the only Chriſtian ſacrifice we have, but to deliver himſelf as if the Maſſes had been offer'd up to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62701:18"/> Cardinal, and not to God the only Ruler of mens hearts.</p>
            <p n="31">31. Soon after S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was choſen General of the Society; <hi>which he accepted with as many Teares and proteſtations and intreaties,</hi> (ſaies the Dr. <hi>till he plainly ſaw it was the will of God, as ever any Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per took the Government into his hands, which he had moſt eagerly ſought for.</hi> Fy upon't! this is rudeneſs in a high degree. A civil perſon would hardly give a dog ſuch language, if any perſon of quality had a kindneſs for him, as he gives S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who has the eſteem of a great Saint in the opinion of moſt of the greateſt Princes and Monarchs of the Chriſtian world. Had it not been ſufficient to expreſs his ambition, to have ſaid, that he long'd as much for the Generalſhip, as a hungry Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter newly come from the Univerſity, does for a good Benefice or as a friend of his does for a Biſhopprick? but he muſt compare him to a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oud Uſurper. But where is his Author for this calumny? he does not produce ſo much as a <hi>Schioppious</hi> to juſtify it. Let any indifferent perſon take but the pains to read over the Saints life, and I am very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident he will find, that no man could labour more to decline Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority than he did, nor to ſhake it off when it was in his hands, ſo far was he from ſeeking it. He muſt have been a prodigious Hypocrite, that could preach and profeſs ſo much humility, and bind his followers by expreſs vow, not to ſeek any ſuch honour, <hi>directly or indirectly,</hi> and yet ſeek it himſelf, with ſuch eagerneſs as the Dr. expreſſes. But he may do well to tell us how he ſaught it: was it openly or covertly; if openly, it was the certain way to loſe it, and we have no record of any ſuch thing; if covertly, how comes the Dr. to ſmell out his knavery, which no body has yet diſcovered beſides himſelf, and thoſe of his privy Counſel.</p>
            <p n="32">32. He concludes his Libel with a whole peal of injuries. Take them as they lye. <hi>Let the world judge</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>whether there has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a greater Enthuſiaſtick, or pretender to revelations then</hi> Ignatius <hi>was ſince the dayes of</hi> Mahomet <hi>and</hi> S. Francis. I will not here diſpute ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unworthily he couples <hi>Mahomet</hi> and S. <hi>Francis</hi> together, that is, a Turk and a Chriſtian, a Divel and a great Saint. Thoſe of his holy Order will not fail to vindicate their glorious Patriark. Nor will I quarrel with him, for comparing S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> with that Seraphical Saint in point of <hi>enthuſiaſme.</hi> But becauſe he takes that word in the worſt ſence for <hi>Fanaticiſme</hi> my inquiry ſhall only be upon what evidence he makes S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> a <hi>Fanatick.</hi> I have run over as much of his life as he thought worth his gloſſing; I have conſidred it leiſurely, and by parts, and have not yet found any thing, that looks like an argument
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62701:19"/> to prove ſo great a Paradox, and certainly if his particular actions, do not prove it, he will never do it by <hi>accumulation.</hi> But he appeals to the judgement of the <hi>world: let the world judge.</hi> I marvail what he means by the <hi>world.</hi> Turks, Jews and Pagans, or only Chriſtians? the firſt are not competent judges, the latter will be ſure to caſt him; for amongſt Chriſtians, the far major part is Catholick, and honours him for a great Saint, ſo that the Dr. will come ſhort of his aim. But tis like he means only <hi>England</hi> which <hi>being divided from all the world,</hi> makes a little world by it ſelf, and probably is all the world he has ſeen. If this be his meaning, ſet a ſide all thoſe, whom he calls Fanaticks and Sectaries, and his <hi>world</hi> will dwindle away into a very Microcoſme. But I refuſe not to be tryed by my country, provided that he have not the impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelling of the Jury<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and will but give men leave to be rational crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that is, lead by reaſon and common ſenſe, and not hurried away with prejudice and paſſion, Let us then ſee what evidence he brings. The ſtrength of his accuſation lies in this, that, <hi>he was a great preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Viſions and Revelations.</hi> He means a falſe <hi>pretender,</hi> for otherwiſe to own or acknowledge ſuch favours received at Gods hand, is no more than what the beloved Diſciple of Jeſus, S. <hi>Peter,</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> S. <hi>Steven,</hi> and <hi>Ananias</hi> did amongſt the firſt Chriſtians, as is plainly to be ſeen in the holy Scripture, and yet the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. will not offer to make them <hi>Fanaticks.</hi> To theſe I could add a world of others within the firſt four Centuries after Chriſt, but will confine my ſelf to produce but a few of them. If we give credit to the antient Records, S. <hi>Cicely</hi> ſaw her good Angel, and ſo did her ſpouſe <hi>Valerianus,</hi> and his B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>other <hi>Tibur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> all famous Martyrs. S. <hi>Martin</hi> had often the like favour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and whilſt he was but a Catechumen, ſaw Chriſt in that part of his Cloak, which he had parted from the reſt, to beſtow upon a poor beggar. S. <hi>Agatha's</hi> breaſt was cured in an apparition of S. <hi>Peter.</hi> The great S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was miraculouſly call'd by a voyce, that ſaid <hi>take up and read. Confeſ. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> had a whiſpering Angel at his ear, and ſaw Chriſt our Saviour a little before his death, as <hi>Paulinus</hi> witneſſeth in his life, which he ſayes he writ at the intreaty of S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Our B Lady, and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> appeared to S. <hi>Gregory Thaumaturgus,</hi> and taught him the Myſtery of the moſt B. Trinity, as witneſſeth S. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen.</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> B Saviour appeared to S. <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> in a torn garment, and ſaid it was <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rius</hi> that had ſo wrent it by his Schiſme. S. <hi>Dorothy</hi> had Apples and Roſes ſent her from Heaven, a little before her Martyrdome. You ſee all theſe Saints of the Primitive Church own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or <hi>pretended Viſions and Revelations,</hi> and muſt therefore be <hi>Fanaticks</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62701:19"/> as well as St, <hi>Ignatius.</hi> And <hi>Conſtantin</hi> the great <hi>[Euſeb. in vita Conſta<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>]</hi> the glory of our Nation muſt go with the reſt, for pretending to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſht by St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> to ſend for St. <hi>Sylveſter</hi> Pope, to waſh away his Leproſie with the VVater of Baptiſm, and for ſeeing (together with his whole Army) the ſign of the Croſs in the Air, with this Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>in this ſign thou ſhalt overcome,</hi> [in act <hi>Silveſt,</hi> and for having another Viſion the ſame night, in which Chriſt commanded him to arm himſelf with that ſign, which he inſtantly did by placing it in his Standard and upon his Helmet. It is not then the bare <hi>pretence</hi> of having <hi>Viſions,</hi> that can prove St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> a <hi>Fanatick</hi> more then other Saints, who for all their <hi>Viſions,</hi> have the general reputation of Sanctity. It muſt then be a falſe or counterfeit <hi>pretence</hi> of them, which the Dr. does not ſo much as offer to prove, but by his own uncharitable ſuppoſitions: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which we have Miracles enough, and other arguments of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs to prove him a Saint, and conſequently to juſtifie the truth of his Viſions; if any credit be to be given, to the juridical Proceſs made in order to his Canonization, which cannot be queſtion'd, unleſs we rob the World of all Faith and Honeſty. Let not the Dr. then tell me, his Miracles may be as well queſtion'd as hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Viſions; for I challenge him, to produce any Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them which <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtata</hi> might not have urg'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Miracles of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. One thing I muſt not here omit to tell you, that St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was alwayes known, to be very reſerv'd in ſpeaking of the extraordinary favours of Almighty God, but when he ſaw it was for his greater glory to manifeſt them; in ſo much, that he commanded his ghoſtly Father, upon pain of excommunication and diſmiſſion out of the Society, not to reveal any thing in this kind, that might tend to his praiſe. But he did ſome things like the Quakers, and ſo does the Dr. too, and may as well prove him a Quaker, becauſe he had a noſe on his face, as becauſe he did not for a time uſe to put off his Hat. For as that is no Argument, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe others have Noſes as well as Quakers, ſo does not this conclude, becauſe there are others that do not uſe civilities, as well as Quakers, to wit, Clowns, and thoſe that for juſt Reaſons perſonate them, as <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> did for a time, out of humility, to conceal his condition, and give occaſion of being flighted, and contemned in all Companies, as a mean ill bred Perſon. There was a time when our dread Soveraign, was fain to paſs under the diſguize of an ordinary Servant; ſure the Doctor will not thence conclude him, to be of a mean condition becauſe he once acted that part. Say his Majeſty had thought
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62701:20"/> fit, under that Maſque, not to put off his Hat, ſhall he be a Quaker too? The Argument were as good as that which he brings againſt St. <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">33. He goes on. <hi>The chiefeſt of the Quakers, fall very much ſhort of</hi> St. <hi>Ignatius in thoſe very things for which they are condemned by us.</hi> I pray what are thoſe things? beſides his not putting off his Hat (for the Reaſons I mentioned) I can find nothing in all his Life, which did not become a Saint. <hi>Yet any one,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>who compares them would imagine, the Life of</hi> Ignatius <hi>had been their great Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar.</hi> In what I pray? was he not a Roman Catholick, and do not all Catholicks cry down <hi>Fanaticiſme</hi> did he ever hold any of the Quakers fond Tenets? did he deny Infant Baptiſm, or rely upon a private Spirit, in oppoſition to the Churches Doctrine, or refuſe to be guided by his Superiours and ſpiritual Directors? nay do not the Authors of his Life take notice, that he had recourſe to his ghoſtly Fathers, and followed their Directions in the change of his Life in his Scruples, in admirting the Generalſhip in all doubtful occaſions, and particularly at the hour of his death? Did he ever profeſs himſelf to be Chriſt as <hi>Iames Nayler</hi> did? Again what Quaker ever followed him, in leaving all to follow the Counſels of Chriſt, in voluntary poverty, chaſtity and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience? What Quaker ever took ſo much pains to get learning as he did, or thought it neceſſary, to do good with his Neighbour? What Quaker lead ſuch an auſtere penitential Life as he, or ſpent ſo much time in Pray'r on his Knees, and in the Night; or beg'd from Door to Door, in a poor Pilgrims habit? What Quaker ever ſuffered ſo many Perſecutions, and came off ſo clear in the judgement of his Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors? What Quaker converted ſo many millions from Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme as he has done by his Diſciples? Laſtly, what Quaker had ſuch illuſtrious marks of Sanctity as he, atteſted upon Oath by Witneſs beyond Exception, and approved by the See Apoſtolick? Let us follow him. <hi>I know not whether any of that Innocent and Religious Order of Ieſuits, had any hand in forming this new Society</hi> (he means Quakers) <hi>among us as has been frequently ſuggeſted.</hi> I know not whether the Dr. were in his wits, when he writ this, which no ſober Perſon can any more believe, then that it was a Jeſuite, that taught the Serpent in Paradiſe, to pull a curſe upon all mankind, by cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly circumventing our firſt Parents. The thing was merrily ſaid, by a Perſon of quality in <hi>France,</hi> when he heard the Jeſuites ſlandred, but the Dr. if he pleaſe, may object it in his next Book, unleſs he had rather leave it to his Freind, the Author of the Anſwer to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62701:20"/> Apology, who it ſeems, is putting out another terrible knocking Book againſt the Jeſuites, for it will come in well there. But have patience to hear him out. <hi>If one may gueſs the Father by the Child's likeneſs,</hi> Ignatius Loyola <hi>Founder of the Ieſuites, was at leaſt the Grandfather of the Quakers.</hi> I have already ſhew'd you how like, or rather how unlike they are. I am quite weary of ſuch pittiful Stuff. <hi>Let the World now judge,</hi> how well the Dr. has acquitted himſelf of his promiſe <hi>pag.</hi> 262, of making St. <hi>Ignatius appear as great a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick as ever has been in the World,</hi> and whether according to the ſame promiſe he is to be <hi>contented to be upbraided with the charge of Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſme.</hi> At leaſt I laid it at his Door in my firſt Letter, and there it is like to lie together with <hi>Idolatry,</hi> till he know how to remove them, without changing his <hi>Principles.</hi> Let this ſuffice to vindicate St. <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> in my next Letter you ſhall hear of his Followers.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="letter">
            <head>THE THIRD LETTER, <hi>That the Jeſuits Doctrine and Practiſes, are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Government.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">1. THe Jeſuites had no reaſon to expect, that after Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet</hi> had dealt ſo rudely with St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> their holy Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (as you have ſeen) he would uſe them with more civility. And they are wiſe enough to bleſs God for it. For they take it for a great argument of his Love to their Order, to permit it to be abuſed by malitious Tongues, as well as to be cried up by a good People, as a ſeaſonable recruit and ſupport in the Church, in theſe later times. They adore Gods Providence and know it is the ſtyle of his infinite Wiſdom, to expoſe his own works to rough tryals, to render them more illuſtrious; that the Devil uſes all his Engines to deſtroy them;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62701:21"/> and that the world follows the method, and intention of the Devil his Maſter. There is not a holier Society upon Earth then Chriſts Church, nor was there ever any which ſuffered greater ſlaunders then She has done, both in her Head and Members. Chriſt was traduced for an Impoſter, a Seducer an Enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> a ſeditious Fellow, a very Divel, and was crucified between two Thieves, to take away his life and reputation at one blow. Chriſtians have ever ſince met with the like treaty. From the beginning they were <hi>every where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted.</hi> Acts 28. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw <hi>a great Door open</hi> to his labours in the converſion of Souls, but he alſo diſcovered a great many Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. others that followed him were accuſed for Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Infants, devourers of mans Fleſh, Enemies to the State, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous and abominable Wretches, and for ſuch were put to cruel deaths. Sacred and profane Hiſtory is full of Examples of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and no body can queſtion what I have ſaid, that is not a meer Stranger to them. Yet could there be a juſter or holier man, then the Son of God, the Holy of Holies, and Juſtice it ſelf were there ever Perſons more eſtranged from Cruelty, Sedition and Impurity, or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Lovers of Peace, Meekneſs and Chaſtity, then thoſe Chriſtians? Why then did God permit the Divel and the World ſo furiouſly to miſuſe his Son and his Servants? To give their Vertue a greater lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, after ſuch hard tryals, to ſhew that truth triumphs over all the Powers of Hell, and to Crown their ſufferings with immortal Laurels. That which happened to Chriſt and his Church in general, has befaln all Religious Orders in their firſt riſe. The <hi>Benedictines, Carthuſians, Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, Franciſcans,</hi> have all had their ſhare in ſufferings, they have all been filed, and poliſhed with the ſharp Teeth of wicked Slaunderers, nor will our Adverſaries yet let them be quiet, as you ſee. The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Jeſus as it came laſt into the World, ſo has it been more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted then all the reſt, for as much as the World is grown more inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate in malice, and the Divel more enraged, at the good which he ſees dayly wrought by their pious endeavours; What miſchief has there been in this laſt age, whereof the Jeſuits have not been made the chief Authors and Contrivers, as if they had opened <hi>Pandora</hi>'s Box, and let all evils into the World. But for their comfort, they can be treated no worſe then their dear Maſter, who has read them this Leſſon, <hi>as they have perſecuted me, ſo will they perſecute you.</hi> And they may well apply that of <hi>Origin.</hi> to themſelves. <hi>Hom.</hi> 11. <hi>Ioſua. He that ſeeks the Freindſhip of Ieſus, let him know he ſhall have many Enemies, Though you be of the leaſt merit in the Church,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:62701:21"/> 
               <hi>yet if you belong to Ieſus, you ſhall be ſure to be perſecuted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is not my intention at preſent to make my ſelf Protectour or all thoſe illuſtrious Religious Orders (as the Dr. ſeems to have made himſelf Champion of the Engliſh Proteſtant Church) They are able to defend themſelves againſt all their Adverſaries. Nor do I mean to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in all the Jeſuits quarrels, but onely for your ſatisfaction, wipe off that Dirt which the Dr. has lately caſt upon them. I reduce all his Calumnies to three Heads. Firſt I briefly examin the Jeſuits Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Practiſes, and ſhew them not to be deſtructive to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that ſhall be my Task in this Letter. In the next I will make it appear that they are neither Factious nor Enemies to Biſhops, and then I will alſo remove a libellous ſtory of the Jeſuits way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting <hi>China.</hi> I confeſs I do not admire their modeſty, for not appearing all this while in defence of their Order, for the violence of their Enemies is come to ſuch a height, there's no diſſembling it. Their patience may be very laudable in other occaſions, but not when the reputation of their inſtitute lies at ſtake. Methinks they ſhould reflect upon the Counſel which his Majeſty's Grandfather <hi>Henry</hi> 4. (that wiſe King) gave the <hi>French</hi> Jeſuits, after he had ſtudied them well. <hi>Fathers,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>make but your ſelves known, for no body that knows the Society can ſpeak ill of it.</hi> I know they cannot flatter themſelves ſo much as to think, they can with their writings ſtop the wide mouths of envy and malice, yet may they ſo far vindicate the Society, that Sober Perſons will ſee they are wronged, and happily ſome Proteſtants upon better information, may grow to be of our great Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of <hi>England,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Bacons</hi> opinion, who <note place="margin">Bacon <hi>advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </note> ſaid of the Jeſuits, that when he conſidered their pains and induſtry in advancing Learning, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Youth, that of <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> came to his mind, <hi>talis cum ſis utinam noſter eſſes.</hi> By theſe few Sheets which have rob'd me only of ſome ſpare hours you may ſee how eaſily it were for a good Pen, to juſtifie the Jeſuits in a Cauſe, where innocency pleads for them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For methods ſake I begin with the Jeſuits Principles, and then proceed to their practiſes: In both charges I promiſe to diſſemble nothing which the Dr. has objected, if it any way concern the Jeſuits, but make bold to wave ſome impertinent matters, which he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixes, as that of the Iriſh Remonſtrance, Pope's proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:62701:22"/> 4. The firſt principle which he faſtens upon the Jeſuits, as deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to government, is, that civil power is ſo originally in the people, that they may in ſome caſes, alter the form of government, if they find it neceſſary for the good and preſervation of the common-wealth. This principle (whatſoever truth it may have in ſpeculation) is by no means to be preached to the people, who are apt enough of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſtretch caſes, and pick quarrels with their beſt Governours, yet was it taught many ages before the Jeſuites were ſo much a thought of. And as the Dr. confeſſes that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> uſes <hi>Navarr</hi> for it (who was no Jeſuit) ſo he might have produced many more, as well Divines as Lawyers; and amongſt others, <hi>Barclay</hi> himſelf allows it may be practiſed in two caſes, as Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> has well obſerved. And ſince there are ſo many precedents, where the people have aſſumed the power, it had been very <note place="margin">Oration to the third ſtate.</note> ſtrange if no body had ſtood up in defence of it, had it been but to juſtifie their Princes Title, who were beholding to the people for them. What then if a few Jeſuits have followed this opinion, which they found taught by others, and what if Father <hi>Parſons</hi> had been one of theſe? is it therefore to be pinn'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Jeſuits, as their particular doctrine? The opinion may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led any thing as well as <hi>Ieſuitical,</hi> I will call it <hi>Proteſtant</hi> if you pleaſe, for this laſt age, has afforded us more examples of the doctrine put in practiſe amongſt Proteſtants, then many ages have done before, as is demonſtrated at large in that excellent Hiſtorical Treatiſe <hi>Hieruſalem and Babel.</hi> Did not thoſe of the Reformation actually turn out their Soveraign Princes, in <hi>Scotland, Swedland Denmark, Holland</hi> and <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva?</hi> Did they not raiſe Tumults, and Rebellions in <hi>France, Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Poland, Hungary, Bohemia, Tranſilvania?</hi> did not <hi>brave Coligny</hi> (as the Drs. worthy Author of the Anſwer to the Papiſts Apology ſtyles him) head the Rebels in <hi>France,</hi> and brag he had loſt four bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, againſt the King, and yet was formidable? did not <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt with his councel, give away Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Title, to the Lady <hi>Iane Grey,</hi> and did not <hi>Cranmer</hi> and <hi>Ridley</hi> ſtickle hard for her? were there not more Rebellions in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> five years reign, then in forty under Queen <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> Was not Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Heir of the Crown of <hi>England</hi> and was ſhe not put to death, leaſt ſhe ſhould deſtroy the Proteſtant Religion, as the Earl of <hi>Kent</hi> told her? <hi>Cambden,</hi> 1587. <hi>pag.</hi> 455. Were not all theſe Factions and Rebellious proceedings, warranted by their own Proteſtant Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, <hi>Luther, Calvin, Beza, Zuinglius, Knox, Bucanan, Douglaſs, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:62701:22"/> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to return again to Father <hi>Parſons,</hi> the Dr. makes it ſure, that he writ <hi>Doleman,</hi> but he had moſt reaſon to know that himſelf, and I have alwaies heard, that he denyed it at his death, and that one <hi>Doleman,</hi> (no Jeſuit) was the Author of that book; there are no few arguments to prove, that Father <hi>Parſons</hi> was not the man. But whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it was, it is fooliſhly done of the Dr. to make him guilty of the late Kings blood. He has a great deal more reaſon to lay it upon <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> and other ſeditious Proteſtant Preachers, who though they might borrow part of <hi>Dolemans</hi> diſcourſe, yet ſcorn'd to be beholding to him for the doctrine. You ſee, Sir, the Anſwerers of <hi>Philanax,</hi> and the Papiſts Apology, will receive but little benefit from this obſervation, which Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> has added to theirs, when they come to their more <hi>accurate examinations</hi> of theſe things.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Another Jeſuitical principle (of the Drs. making) is the Popes power to depoſe Princes. This is every where laid in their diſh, by him and his party; but with a great deal of injuſtice, as you ſhall preſently ſee. You are then to know, Sir, that the doctrine was long agoe taught by almoſt all Orders and Profeſſions, Seculars, Regulars, Divines, Lawyers, before the Jeſuits were in being. <hi>Card. Perron</hi> in his Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Oration, to the third State in <hi>France,</hi> quotes ſome of them, and <hi>Barclay</hi> calls it the Canoniſts, and Divines common Doctrine. I will not tire you out, with a tedious Catalogue of Authors, ſome of thoſe who are wont to be cited are, <hi>Panormiranus, Aegidius Rom.</hi> St. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Cajetan</hi> St. <hi>Bonaventure, Halenſis, Waldenſis, Bacon, Gerſon</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of <hi>Paris, Sanders, Bartholus, Bardus, &amp;c.</hi> What wonder then if <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and three or four more Jeſuits, were carryed away with ſuch a torrent of Doctors who went before them. They found their works publickly expos'd it Libraries, never cenſur'd, but in good repute amongſt the Learned, nor had Princes in thoſe dayes ſhewed their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt their doctrine as they have done ſince. What won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I ſay, then, if a few Jeſuits have ſince followed it? Is this ſufficient to excuſe the Dr. from wilful malice or groſs ignorance, in attributing the opinion to the whole Society, as if the <hi>whole Herd of Ieſuits</hi> (as the miſcalls them) had taught it, and no body in the world but they. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive it, Sir, there is no man that has a grain of judgement, but will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the Jeſuits of all others can be the leaſt charged with it not only becauſe it was the common doctrine, before they came into the world, but alſo becauſe (whatſoever others have done) they have taught it, nor writ one word of that ſubject, theſe fifty or ſixty years. For no ſooner was the doctrine cryed down, and condemn'd in <hi>France,</hi> but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62701:23"/> their General <hi>Cladius Aquaviva,</hi> to take away all occaſion of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, forbad it to be taught any more; and his Succeſſor <hi>Mutius Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telleſchi A. D.</hi> 1626. not content with a bare prohibition, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all his Subjects in vertue of obedience (that is under pain of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation) never to treat more of the Popes power of depoſing Princes either in word or in writing. And this precept was afterwards confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the whole Order in the 8 general Congregation, and runs thus. <hi>We ordain in vertue of holy obedience, that no body hereafter, treat the queſtion of the Popes power over Princes, to depoſe them, &amp;c. in any publick or private writings, diſputations or School leſſons, that all occaſion of offence and complaint may be quite cut off.</hi> This decree has been ever ſince inviolably obſerved by the Jeſuits, let the Dr. either name the perſons that has tranſgreſſed, or let him forbear hereafter to make the Jeſuits odious, for a doctrine which they have ſo ſolemnly renounced. He would take it ill to have all the Proteſtant Miniſters Tenets layd at his door. <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> ſaid well in his ſpeech to the Parliament. <hi>I am certain that in averring and defending the Popes authority, the Fathers of the Society differ not from other Catholick Divines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. A third, and yet more dangerous and deſperate Principle, which the Dr. fathers on the Jeſuits, is the lawfulneſs to kill Kings. I cannot name the perſon that ever taught it in theſe termes. I know <hi>Dominious Soto</hi> a Dominican, <hi>Charles</hi> 5 Confeſſor, taught it lawful to take away the lifo of a Tyrant, <hi>(l.</hi> 1. <hi>de jure &amp; juſt.)</hi> and <hi>Mariana</hi> followed him in a book dedicated to <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and neither of thoſe Princes took themſelves to be concern'd in the opinion, or ſhew'd their diſpleaſure againſt the book, no more than the Royaliſts were offended at <hi>Killing no Murther.</hi> But it ſeems <hi>Marcan's</hi> book gave great offence in <hi>France.</hi> And all the Jeſuits ſinned in him (as we all did in <hi>Adam)</hi> otherwiſe his doctrine, which they diſown, would not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to them. The French Fathers were the firſt that diſcovered it in <hi>Mariana's</hi> book, and condemn'd it in their Provintial Congregation, four years before the <hi>Sorbon</hi> cenſure was paſſed againſt it. And their General <hi>Claudius Aquaviva,</hi> gave order to ſuppreſs the book, till that place were corrected; and more than this, forbad all thoſe of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, under pain of excommunication, and other penalties (as is to be ſeen in the 8 Congregation, <hi>Tit. cenſurae)</hi> not to write or teach in publick or private, or adviſe that it is lawful to kill Kings, or imagine their death upon pretence of Tyranny, ſo that very probably this extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant opinion of <hi>Mariana,</hi> by the Jeſuits induſtry, would have been ſo ſmothered in its firſt birth; as not to be revived, had it not been for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62701:23"/> the covetouſneſs, or malice of the Proteſtant Heirs of <hi>Wechel</hi> who reprinted the Book at their own charges. I owe this Obſervation to Father <hi>Cotton,</hi> who in his Letter to the Queen Regent of <hi>France</hi> brings in a whole Jury of Jeſuits, who in their Writings have all rejected the opinion and practiſe, of attempting any thing againſt the Life of a Prince, though he ſhould abuſe His Princely Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Theſe are all grave Writers, <hi>Tolet, Bellarmin, Valentia, Salme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Delrio, Heiſſius, Becanus, Gretſer, Leſſius, Serarius, Azor, Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</hi> All other Jeſuits ſide with theſe, and are ready to ſeal it with their Blood, that the Decree of the Council of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſs.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtance</hi> ought to be received by all, and maintained invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably. This being the conſtant judgement of the whole Society, what prejudice can one roving Pen, bring to the whole Order. <hi>Iohn Wicklef</hi> is a rubricated St. in <hi>Foxe</hi>'s Proteſtant Calendar, and yet the ſaid Council condemn'd him for teaching that, <hi>every Tyrant ought to be kill'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that it was both lawful and meritorious, for any of his Vaſſals or Subjects to kill him, and that by any fraud or deceit, notwithſtanding any Oath or Agreement made to the contrary, and that without any Sentence of Iudgement.</hi> Luther, Calvin, Beza, Buchanan, did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teach the ſame Propoſitions, but moſt impudently applied them to Princes then living, namely to <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> Queen Mother with all her Whelps, as they call'd her Children, Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. and yet the Dr. with Reaſon would think himſelf much injured if theſe mad Propoſitions of <hi>Wicklef</hi> and others, were lay'd to his Church of <hi>England,</hi> for all they were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and ſome of them cannonized for Saints by Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> with what Face then can he lay the fault of one Jeſuit to the whole Order, as if it were an original Sin, which were to deſcend to all Jeſuits though their wills were ſo far from being united with his, that they have expreſly renounced and condemned his raſh aſſertion. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this method, it were no hard matter to ruin the reputation of the beſt Families and Communities in the World, by making them guilty of their miſdemeanours of ſome one of their Body contrary to the judgement of Almighty God Ezek. 18. 20. <hi>The Soul that ſhall ſin, the ſame ſhall die: the Son ſhall not bear the iniquity of the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The Jeſuites practiſes are conformable to the Doctrine and Practiſe of the Catholick Church, but the Dr. ſuppoſes them guilty of moſt abominable crimes. I ſay ſuppoſes, for he brings nothing to prove it beſides his <hi>Ipſe dixit,</hi> or bare aſſertion, which as you have
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62701:24"/> ſeen, is not only fallible, but has been often found tripping, Firſt he ſuppoſes them to have had a hand in the maſſacre at <hi>Paris,</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> which is as true, as that they were the Plotters and Contrivers of the late Rebellion in <hi>England,</hi> where their penitents and beſt Freinds, loſt their Goods, or their Lives in the defence of His Majeſties Power and juſt Rights. The Maſſacre at <hi>Paris</hi> was an intrigne of State, or Cabinet plot, as appears by all the Tranſactions faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Recorded by D. <hi>Avila,</hi> and never was laid to the Jeſuites charge, who hate ſuch unchriſtian like Proceedings. They are as innocent of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion, for what Jeſuit can the Dr. name that appeared in it? certainly they had not play'd their Cards well to raiſe a Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> and at the ſame time promote to their uttermoſt, His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's intereſt in <hi>England.</hi> I confeſs Catholicks in that Kingdom were highly to blame, but they ſtirr'd not before Proteſtants had ſign'd and delivered a bloody Petition to the Parliament, for their utter extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation or baniſhment. And the Author of the <hi>Polititians</hi> Catechiſm proves at large, 6. 10. <hi>n.</hi> 6. that Proteſtants had a greater hand then Catholicks in theſe cruel diſorders.</p>
            <p n="8">8. His ſecond charge againſt the Jeſuits in point of practiſe runs yet higher; for he makes them privy Counſellors to three of the greateſt Parricids in the world, <hi>Clement, Chaſtel</hi> and <hi>Ravillas.</hi> Never was there ſo much malice crouded into one line, but it will coſt me many Lines to clear the Jeſuits from that riple crime; for I cannot do it but by giving you a ſhort Narrative of theſe three treaſonable attemps. To begin with <hi>Clement,</hi> the murtherer of <hi>Henry</hi> 3. of <hi>France,</hi> the Caſe is clear, he was no Jeſuit nor had he any other Counſellour that we know of but the Divel to ſet him at work. I think the Dr. is the firſt man that ever named the Jeſuits in that wicked fact. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God forgive him for it.</p>
            <p n="9">9. For <hi>Chaſtel</hi> it is true, Sir, the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> and the Churches common enemies have blazed about many ſtories; as if they had been acceſſary to his execrable attempt upon the life of <hi>Henry</hi> 4. but if any credit be to be given to the <hi>French</hi> Hiſtorians due <hi>Pleix, Peter, Matthew, de Ton, Spodanus</hi> and others, or to the grave Counſellors who pleaded for the Jeſuits before the Parliament; <hi>Rene de la Fon,</hi> and <hi>Montholon,</hi> or to the Kings own teſtimony, who was moſt of all concerned to know the truth, they are moſt ſhamefully ſlaundered. This is the true Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. One <hi>Iohn Chaſtel</hi> wounded the King in the upper Lip and ſtruck out one of his Teeth. He was taken in the Fact and confeſs'd all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was led to Priſon: that he did it of his own head; without communicating
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62701:24"/> his deſign with any body, only ſomething a far off to his father; that it was eight months ſince he had left the Jeſuits Schooles, and that they knew not any thing of his intentions. All this he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed freely and without compulſion. The ſame ſtory he repeated again and again in Priſon, and though often cruelly rack'd and tortured to declare his councellours and complices, never varied in the leaſt from what he confeſſed at firſt, nor let one word fall againſt the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its. And there were thouſands of witneſſes in the place of Execution, that when his arms and thighs were cruelly pinched, his hand cut off, and all humane means uſed to extort the truth from him, he perſiſted ſtill in the ſame confeſſion and dyed upon't, declaring the Jeſuits inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to the laſt breath. Yet for all this, becauſe he had once frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Jeſuits ſchooles, their malicious enemies, would needs forſooth conclude thence that they were plotters of the miſcheif. Away then they go armed to their Colledge, ſet guards at the Gates that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhould eſcape; ſeize on their perſons, ranſack their chambers, but diſcover nothing either in their carriages or their countenances, that could argue a guilty conſcience; but rather all the ſigns and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of innocency; only becauſe amongſt other writings of Father <hi>Guignard,</hi> they found the common queſtion, <hi>de Tirannicidio,</hi> which was writ in the time of the League, and which Canoniſts and moral Philoſophers were wont to treat much in thoſe dayes, and which <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din</hi> amongſt modern Authors thought fit to diſpute in his Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, they took him and hang'd him up for a Traytour without any form or order of Juſtice, ſay the Authors. And in the ſame fury they led away <hi>Gueret,</hi> who had been <hi>Chaſtel's</hi> Maſter, and put him upon the rack, but finding him innocent they baniſhed him out of <hi>France,</hi> and all the Jeſuits for company, with confiſcation of their goods: and to make them eternally infamous, they erected a Pyramid with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, tending more to their diſgrace, then the Kings honour. This ſentence of <hi>Paris</hi> was executed in moſt places of <hi>France,</hi> only the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> look't upon it as an unjuſt Act, and forbade all townes under their juriſdiction to obey it. This is the ſumm of that Tragical ſtory, which ſerves well for the Jeſuits juſtification, for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſpeaking it was impoſſible, that <hi>Chaſtel</hi> ſhould not have accuſed the Jeſuits, had he known them guilty. He that made no difficulty to accuſe himſelf and bring his own father upon the ſtage, why ſhould he ſtick to accuſe the Jeſuits? is it credible that a youth of eighteen years age ſhould undergo a thouſand torments worſe then death, rather then acknowledge the Authors of his ſufferings, when we have heard
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62701:25"/> of men that were made of Iron, who rather choſe to accuſe themſelves wrongfully and dye once for all, than ſuffer ſo many lingring deaths upon the Rack? It was queſtionleſs a moſt admirable and miraculous price of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ovidence over the Jeſuits, that he did not unjuſtly accuſe them, when he was ſo many wayes tempted to do it, for one ſyllable would have done their buſineſs, had it been upon the rack, had it been afterwards recall'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it would have ſerv'd to ruine them utterly, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their lives and fortunes, but in their credit and reputation, which is far dearer to them; for if a meer ſhadow of preſumption gave their adverſaries the boldneſs to charge them and treat them ſo ſeverely; what were they to have expected, had the force of torments made them criminals? true or falſe it would never have been then much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted.</p>
            <p n="10">10. You may imagine the King himſelf would be curious to ſift out the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uth, whether indeed the Jeſuits had a hand in that ſtroak, which aim'd at his life. He ſoon diſcover'd the malice of their accuſers, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſcarce got the Reins of Government into his hands, he thought fit to diſſemble for a time; but upon occaſion of a ſtudyed bitter invect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive, which the Preſident <hi>Harley</hi> made in Parliament, to perſuade his Majeſty not to think of recalling the Jeſuits, he ſuddenly took upon him to plead their cauſe, and did it with ſo much Wiſdome and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that they could not have choſen a better advocate. The Speech is worth your reading, and therefore I ſend it with this Letter that you may peruſe it. The concluſion was, that the Jeſuits were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, and the infamous Pyramid pull'd down by the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; who not content to have re-eſtabliſhed them in their own Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, built and founded them a ſtately Colledge and Academy at <hi>La Fleche,</hi> and bequeathed his heart to them as a perpetual monument of his conſtant Love to the Society. And that you may here alſo read his affection for them in his own language. I think it not amiſs to inſert that Speech of his, which he made at <hi>Villiers-Coterez, A. D.</hi> 1606. to the Fathers that were deputed by the Provincial Congregation, to give his Majeſty thanks for his continual favours, and to Petition for two things, firſt, that as he had been graciouſly pleaſed to recall them to <hi>Paris,</hi> he would alſo ſettle and eſtabliſh them there by his Letters Patents. Secondly that he would order that the publick Schools might be reſtored at <hi>Clermont</hi> Colledge. Upon this occaſion he delivered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thus. <hi>Fathers, There are four years paſt ſince you preſented me your welcome Petition at</hi> Metz., <hi>and I did not admit you but upon very good informations, You are beholding to your enemies for it, and my curioſity</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:62701:25"/> 
               <hi>was not out of your way. If things go on but ſlowly, do not attribute it to my want of Affection and care but to the multiplicity of buſineſs, which overwhelmes me. All cannot be done at once, We are now upon the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Colledges, and the reſt will be done by degrees, for I take it to heart. I knew well they were calumnies they caſt upon you. I have alwayes defended you, and when I heard of any thing, I inſtantly acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> F. Cotton <hi>with it, that you might take your meaſures accordingly, and to let you know, that what I did for you, was not out of a counterfeit diſſimulation, but out of My true Love and ſincere Affection. I have placed you in my houſe, and that of my Anceſtors to give my Subjests ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to do the like. Your preſent Petition is grateful. I am reſolved to finiſh my work; but to tell you plainly, I do not think it a fit time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore your Colledge at</hi> Paris: <hi>there will be a time for that hereafter.</hi> Here the King making a Pauſe, the Provincial of the Jeſuits began to mind him of the other thing he had requeſted, and his majeſty immediately replyed. <hi>I am coming to it; but I was willing to begin with that which I take moſt to heart. I remember all you ſaid, though I do not obſerve the ſame method. It is true, you are expoſed in</hi> Paris, <hi>and were I not there, you might come to be affronted but you were too blame you did not tell me ſo, I did not think things went ſo, had I known it, I would have remedied it before this. Give me a note of it, that I may communicate it with my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and get it diſpatcht to day or to morrow. I have loved you and cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you ever ſince I knew you, out of an aſſurance I had, that all thoſe who have recourſe to you, whether for inſtruction in Learning, or for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of their conſciences, are much improved by it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I have alwayes ſayd, that thoſe that truly love and fear God, cannot but do well, and are the moſt faithful to their Princes. Keep but your rules, they are good ones. I have protected you, and will ſtill be your Protector. I am much pleaſed that the Pope does not make you Biſhops and Cardinals: Stick to that, for if ambition once creep in amongſt you, you are loſt men. We are all frail, and have need to reſiſt tentations; every one of you may experience it in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; but you have the way to overcome them. I have a great Kingdome, and as great perſons may commit great errors, or do much good, becauſe they are great and powerful, ſo you that are eminent in Learning and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue amongſt the ſervants of God, may do much good by your Sermons, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, Writings, Leſſons Diſputations, and good inſtructions; but if you fail in your duty, and grow ſlack in your pious endeavours, you may do much hurt, in regard the World has a great opinion of you. I was very glad to underſtand that you have taken order that none of you print books</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:62701:26"/> 
               <hi>which may give offence, you do well. That which might paſs in</hi> Italy, <hi>will not reliſh in other places, and that which is liked in</hi> France, <hi>may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe in</hi> Italy: <hi>We must ſuit our ſelves to thoſe we live with, and you muſt avoid the leaſt occaſion of offence, for there are many eyes upon you and your actions, but it is better for you to be envyed then pittyed. If all bad tongues were cut out, there would be great ſtore of dumb perſons; we ſhould have difficulty to find ſervants. I have been of two Religions, and when I was a</hi> Hugonot, <hi>what ever I did, was ſaid to be done for that party; now I am a Catholick, whatever I do for my Religion, I am ſaid to be a Ieſuit. I ſlight all ſuch ſencures and content my ſelf to do good, becauſe it is good; do you ſo too. Thoſe that ſay it is out of ſpight that you do not restore your Colledge at</hi> Paris, <hi>would ſoon find ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to object againſt you. Do not value what they ſay, but only do well. If in twelve thouſand of you one ſhould chance to commit a fault, it were no great wonder. It were rather a miracle that no more delinquents ſhould be found in ſo great a number, ſince there was one</hi> Iudas <hi>amongſt twelve Apoſtles. This i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le tell you if any one of you commit a fault, I will be the firſt to fall upon him, but will not revenge my ſelf upon the whole body. The Father you have choſe to go to</hi> Rome, <hi>will aſsure your General of my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Society. For your ſelves, you may beleive ile be as tender of you, as of the Apple of my eye. Pray to God for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was His Majeſtyes Speech to the Jeſuits, as it is Recorded by <hi>Montholon</hi> Advocate in Parliament, and what can be added to his teſtimony, whether you regard the perſon that ſpeaks, who was a moſt wiſe Prince: or the ſubſtance he delivers, which is moſt ſententious and ſolid? I do not ſee what Panegyrick or what Apology the Jeſuits could have made of more force or more for their advantage. Their enemies are put upon a neceſſity either to ſpeak well of them, or affront that great Monarch, by giving him the Lye. For to ſay he lov'd the Jeſuits becauſe he did not know them, is to rob him of one of his beſt parts, which all admired in him; which was, not to be eaſily conſened in the judgment he framed of others, and beſides, this was after he had tryed them many years, and had one of them continually near his perſon.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:62701:26"/> 11. After all theſe expreſſions of kindneſs, which were alwayes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with real favours, who would imagine that the Jeſuits ſhould be, I do not ſay, ſo ungrateful and inhumane, but ſo ſtupid and inſenſible of their own good, as to plot this their grand Benenefactors and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors death. Yet Dr. <hi>St.</hi> is the man that layes it to their charge, as if they had not only deſign'd it in <hi>Chaſtels</hi> attempt (which proved ineffectual) but actually murthered him in the perſon of <hi>Ravillac,</hi> of whoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel he ſuppoſes them to have been; though the villain himſelf, who had moſt reaſon to know it, in all his examinations and tortures, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies proteſted, that no body counſaild him to the Fact, nor ſo much as knew of his intentions. It is true the Jeſuits enemies taking it to be a fit occaſion to vent their malice againſt them, during the young Kings minority, whom they could not hurt in his fathers time; ſpread abroad Libels againſt them, and ſtuck not to report that <hi>Ravillac</hi> had ſuck'd all his deadly poyſon out of <hi>Mariana's</hi> book, which he had got by heart: but this engin faild them, for to their great ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, it was found upon due examination, that <hi>Ravillac</hi> knew not a word of Latin in which the book is written, nor ſo much as <hi>Mariana's</hi> name. And ſoon after the Queen Regent, with the Princes and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel in the Kings name, iſſued out a Decree which cleared the Jeſuits from all ſuſpicion of having had any thing to do in that wicked Fact. And becauſe four dayes before the Parliament had condemned Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Bellarmins</hi> book, <hi>de poteſtate ſummi Pontificis in temporalibus,</hi> in the ſame decree they revoked and annulled that Act.</p>
            <p n="12">12. His laſt fling at the Jeſuits practiſe is, to make Father <hi>Henry Garnet</hi> guilty of the Gunpowder Treaſon. But it is manifeſt, that mild man deteſted from his very heart all ſuch bloody practiſes, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all he could to prevent them, by ſuing to <hi>Rome</hi> for an excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, againſt all thoſe that ſhould uſe any violent proceedings upon the account of Religion, as is to be ſeen more at large in the Hiſtory of the Engliſh Province. <hi>(Mar. l.</hi> 7. <hi>an.</hi> 27.) The main thing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt him was his concealing the plot, but you muſt know all the knowledge he had of it, was in the Sacrament of Confeſſion, and all he could do there, was to exhort and conjure his penitent, to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the Plotters from ſo wicked an attempt, and he was not at all wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in this point of duty; but for revealing the plot, it was more than he could do, for Proteſtants muſt give us leave to beleive, what all Catholick Princes and States allow, to be of no prejudice, but rather an advantage to their ſafety; that the Sacred Seal of Confeſſion is invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable, nor is this only the Jeſuits doctrine, but the known opinion of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62701:27"/> all Catholick Divines: there is not that Prieſt amongſt us that will not rather chuſe to dye, than reveal a Confeſſion, and if they dye for it, Proteſtants muſt not think it ſtrange that we honour them. This was Father <hi>Garnets</hi> caſe, who was condemned for not revealing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, and for being a Prieſt and Jeſuit. No wonder then if St. <hi>Arnour</hi> ſaw his picture in a Catholick countrey: But I dare ſay he never ſaw <hi>Guerets</hi> or <hi>Guignards,</hi> as the Dr. inſinuates; for though they dyed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently, yet they dyed not for the Faith, as Father <hi>Garnet</hi> did. Let St. <hi>Arnour</hi> ſay what he will, he never acknowledged himſelf guilty of the Treaſon: that's a meer calumny and it is ſomething ſtrange, the Dr. ſhould travail into <hi>France</hi> to know what paſſed in <hi>London.</hi> All he confeſſed was, that having an inckling of ſuſpicion out of confeſſion that <hi>Catesby</hi> was bruing miſchief (though he knew not what it was) he uſed all his power to perſwade him to be quiet, and not to run him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon deſperate courſes, which were neither pleaſing to God nor man, and that finding him to his thinking, reſolved to follow his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, he did not take himſelf obliged to give informations againſt him, as not judgeing it the part of a chriſtian, much leſs of a Prieſt, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe his brother of a crime, whereof he verily beleived he had repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. After his death it pleaſed God in a wonderful manner to confirme his innocency, <hi>(ibid. n.</hi> 34. 35.) by imprinting his picture upon a husk of ſtraw, where ſome of his blood had light. King <hi>Iames</hi> himſelf and ſome other Proteſtants, as well as many Catholicks were witneſſes of it, and although much endeavour was uſed to find out a Painter, that would undertake to make ſuch another picture by it, none could be found; all concluding it was beyond the art of man, to contrive ſuch a rare peice in ſo narrow a compaſs. The Baron of <hi>Hobocque</hi> (who was then Embaſſador from the Crown of <hi>Spain)</hi> offered ſix hundred Crowns for the ſtraw, and his teſtimony is yet to be ſeen, witneſſing that he ſaw the picture upon it, though he could not ſay it was like Father <hi>Garnet,</hi> becauſe he had never ſeen him. There is alſo extant a large narrative, which one <hi>Iohn Wilkinſon</hi> ſigned at his death, who was the very man that took up the Straw at the Execution, and was alſo preſent when Father <hi>Garnets</hi> picture was firſt diſcovered upon the ſtraw.</p>
            <p n="13">13. One thing more I cannot omit in this place, that if Jeſuits were ſuch deſperate King-haters, as the Dr. paints them, Kings would not be ſuch ſooles as to build them Colledges, and truſt them with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of youth, and with their own Conſciences too, as we ſee moſt Catholick Kings and Princes do to this very day, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62701:27"/> the Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> Queen and Prince Regent of <hi>Portugal,</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans</hi> though but a late convert, Dukes of <hi>Bavary Newburg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and many other Princes of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> and elſe where. It is their neareſt concern to look well to their own preſervation and ſafety, and not to have dangerous Perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them. Had not the Queen Regent of <hi>Spain</hi> taken Jeſuits to be honeſt men, She would never have preferred Father <hi>Nithard</hi> her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour to the firſt Eccleſiaſtical dignity in all <hi>Spain,</hi> She would never have made him her firſt Miniſter of State, Her extraordinary, and now lately her ordinary Embaſſador at <hi>Rome</hi> and procured for him a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Cap, and his Holineſſe's command, and diſpenſation to receive it, and to undertake the other honourable Employments, which he laboured to decline according to the Obligation of his Vow. Believe me Princes are ſo far from conceiving Jeſuits to be Enemies to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that they are generally of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi>'s mind, that they are neceſſary to keep Subjects in obedience to their Governours, and that one of their Colledges is as good as a ſtrong Cittadel, to keep the People in their duty. <hi>[Strad. To.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 3.] And it ſeems the Magiſtrates of <hi>Embrick</hi> in <hi>Cleaveland</hi> thought ſo too; for not many years ago, when the Proteſtant Governour would have turn'd them out of the City, they prevail'd with him to let them ſtay, proteſting that the Jeſuits had ſuch a powerful influence into the good order of the whole Town, that they neither could nor would govern it without them, and with a great deal of reaſon; for what do the Jeſuits Preach to the People, but firſt, that Soveraign Princes are the Lords annointed and therefore to be reſpected and honoured as holy and ſacred things. 2. That it is a damnable Hereſie to think that their power does not come from God. 3. That it is God that ſets the Crown upon their Heads, as it was wont antiently to be repreſented in Pictures by a hand ſtretcht out holding a Crown. 4. That he who reſiſts Kings, purchaſes to himſelf his own damnation, as the Apoſtle expreſſes himſelf. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. 5. That obedience is due to them, not becauſe they are vertuous or wiſe, or indued with any other good quality, but for this only that they are Soveraigns and Gods Vicegerents. 6. that it is not lawful to deny them obedience, much leſs to rebel againſt them although they were vicious, untoward, and hard to ſupport, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 6. 7. That it is a moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious crime &amp; execrable Particide for Subjects to attempt any thing againſt their Perſons, upon any pretence whatſoever, and that afflictions &amp; perſecutions patiently indured, are a moſt grateful Sacrifice unto Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:62701:28"/> 14. What ſhall I now ſay to the Drs. two propoſitions, which he would have Jeſuits declare without mental reſervations? To the firſt, about the Popes power to abſolve Subjects from their obedience, I beg leave to wave ſuch odious controverſies, about the authority of Chriſts Vicar upon earth. Let it ſuffice to have told you with <hi>Henry</hi> 4. that the Jeſuits hold nothing about the Popes power, which is not common to other Catholick Drs. It is not handſome for private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to renounce a power which their Superiours pretend to. To the ſecond, how the Jeſuits would behave themſelves in caſe the Pope ſhould Warr againſt the King, &amp;c. I anſwer, I do not queſtion but his Majeſty would find them faithful Subjects, and repoſe as much truſt in them and all Catholicks, as in Dr. <hi>Sti.</hi> and thoſe of his <hi>Principles.</hi> It is freſh in our memories how the French King, for all he lately ſwagger'd with the Pope, and was ready to make warr againſt him, did not part with the Jeſuit his Confeſſour, nor repoſe leſs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in him and the reſt of his Order. There never was a preſident of the Jeſuits ſiding with his Holineſs againſt their own Princes, but there have been too many Examples of Proteſtants ſiding and Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt their Catholick Princes, We have not forgot the ſetting up the Lady <hi>Iane Greys</hi> title againſt the undoubted Heir of the Crown, and the cutting off the Queen of Scots head, that a Proteſtant might be ſure to ſucceed. It belongs to God to dive into the ſecrets of mens hearts, and therefore I will not offer to judge, but if it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to gueſs by good conjectures, it is ſhrewdly to be ſuſpected, that ſome Proteſtants would have ſcuck to the <hi>good Old Cauſe,</hi> and have been backward enough in his Majeſties happy Reſtauration, had he not been a Proteſtant. I will not puzzle the Dr. with the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch nice caſes, nor give you, Sir, any farther trouble at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but conclude out of the premiſes, that Dr. <hi>Still.</hi> is far from proving the Jeſuits <hi>Fanatical,</hi> for reſiſting Authority under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Religion, which was the thing he undertook to prove. The reſt of his unjuſt accuſations I reſerve for a fourth Letter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:62701:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Speech of</hi> Henry <hi>the IV. King of</hi> France, <hi>in behalf of the</hi> JESUITS.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Nobility of the Court of</hi> Paris <hi>and a great part of the Parliament being come to the Kings Palace,</hi> Harley <hi>one of the Preſidents of the Parliament of</hi> Paris <hi>addreſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his Majeſty, pronounced a ſtudied invective againſt the Jeſuits, wherein he urged all that which the enemies of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety had premeditated. All his ſpeech cloſed in this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Jeſus ought not to be recalled into</hi> France, <hi>but continue baniſht. The King replyed in this manner,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. THe care you ſhew of me and my Kingdome is grateful to me; albeit you ſeem not to have throughly weighed the things you demand, nor are you, as yet, ſo well acquainted with my thoughts, as I am with yours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You deem the Weal of my Kingdome to conſiſt in the propoſition you have made; you tell me it is a matter that deſerves to be moſt carefully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberated. And I tell you, you have ſaid nothing which I have not moſt carefully weighed, and moſt diligently examined by my ſelf theſe eight or nine years.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You take your ſelves for men of great underſtanding and experience in the Common wealth. But beleive me I know as well as You all that hath been in controverſie in this matter.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Firſt of all you object to the Fathers of the Society, the Aſſembly of <hi>Poiſſy,</hi> * but without cauſe. For if there had been at that place others like many of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Clergy held an Aſſembly at</hi> Poiſſy <hi>an.</hi> 1561. <hi>in which the ſociety was allowed of, and admitted though not fully.</hi>
               </note> them, the Catholick cauſe would have had a more happy ſucceſs. Therefore that which you turn to their dispraiſe, any juſt Umpire will attribute to their vertue. But that which I moſt wonder at in your judgements is, that ſo prepoſterouſly you condemn the ſociety of ambition, whereas the Fathers of the Society with a conſtant ſubmiſſion, have ever
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62701:29"/> refuſed all honour and preferment, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Political: and which is more, they bind themſelves by vow not onely not to aſpire to honours, but even to refuſe the ſame when they are freely offered them. Conſider their whole courſe of life, and you ſhall find that all their ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to labour to help all, and that without any pretence of intereſt or gain. They value not the expences of their own pains, ſo they may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit many.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But that you call in queſtion the very name of the Society of Ieſus, and for that you tax them. But ſee with what reaſon. For if they muſt be blamed for that holy name, what ſhall we ſay for thoſe Religious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who take their name from the moſt bleſſed Trinity? And your Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters here at <hi>Paris;</hi> what will you think of them that call themſelves <hi>Daughters of God?</hi> Finally how will you cenſure my Knights, who are called of the Holy Ghoſt? Truly I do not more diſlike them that take their name from Chriſt, then any other.</p>
            <p n="6">6. You object that the Divines of <hi>Sotborn</hi> condemned the Ieſuites. I do not deny it. But they condemned them being innocent, unknown and unheard. For this I call to witneſs, thoſe very Divines themſelves, who now admit them, whom their Predeceſſours baniſhed, and honour them whom they contemned; nay they praiſe now and extol thoſe that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and ſtick not to take them for their Directors, and Maſters, in all kind of Learning.</p>
            <p n="7">7. You tell me the Ieſuits have hitherto remained in <hi>France</hi> onely by connivance, Here I acknowledge, and reverence the divine providence, that hath reſerved this honour for me, not yet atchived by others, that I ſhould eſtabliſh in this Realm the Society of Ieſus, which hitherto hath had no ſetled abode in <hi>France.</hi> My Predeceſſours have received the Society, I will patronize and preſerve them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Peradventure you will turn to the Ieſuits diſcredit, that for which you ought to praiſe and honour them: The Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> earneſtly and openly oppoſed them. And what, I pray, was the cauſe of this oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition? All was, that the Fathers did not only equal others in Learning and Induſtry, but alſo went far beyond them. A clear teſtimony of this is the great number of Youth that frequented the Fathers Schools, where together with Learning they learnt Vertue. But to stop this oppoſition, I will make a Decree that the Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> ſhall no more oppoſe them. And this you will be glad of.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:62701:29"/> 9. But you will tell me, that the ablest of your Parliament got not their Learning of the Ieſuits. This I will not much gain-ſay. For the ableſt of you, as they excel in Learning ſo they exceed in years. Theſe got their Learning in Forreign Nations, before the Society ſet foot in <hi>France.</hi> Others did not ſo, and ſo I am certain they think and ſpeak o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. And what need they ſpeak? the matter it ſelf ſpeaks. We our ſelves ſaw now at the departure of the Society out of <hi>France,</hi> all the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſeemed to depart. Our Univerſitie was deſert and mourned: thoſe came ſeldom at it, who before daily in great numbers frequented the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Yea many departed the Realm, and forſooke their Country to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the Societies Schools; nor could your Decrees or Threats ſtop them.</p>
            <p n="10">10. You ſay the Fathers joyned themſelves to the League, that is not to be imputed to their fault, but to the iniquity of the times. But this I perſwade my ſelf upon the aſſurance I have of the integrity of their Conſciences, that they will become ſuch towards me, as it behoveth them who mindful of benefits, deſire to ſhew themſelves moſt grateful.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Now ſome of you impoſe on the Fathers a new crime, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture as yet unheard of, ſaying, that they draw to their order young men of the most forwardneſs and beſt diſpoſitions. An unpardonable crime: yet I praiſe them and eſteem them particularly for this, that you condemn. Do not we, though in a different matter, do the ſelf ſame? A Captain that is to raiſe Souldiers, does he not cull out the choiceſt, and leave the meaneſt and leaſt hopeful? In your Parliament, when you chooſe a new Court, or fill up an old, do you prefer the unlearnedſt, and leaſt apt for buſineſs? If the Ieſuits ſhould put unlearned Maſters in their Schools, or in their Churches ignorant Preachers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would you not with reaſon blame them? What offence is it that the Ieſuits ſhould provide the fitteſt they can, both for Church and Schools.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That ſlander which concerns the Ieſuits treaſure, is as falſe as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Go viſit all the Colledges in <hi>France,</hi> ſearch all their treaſures ſum all together, and you will ſcarce find twelve, or at moſt fifteen thouſand Crowns I know well how poor and ſlender furniture, and proviſion was both at <hi>Lyons</hi> and <hi>Bourge.</hi> Nevertherleſs 30 or 40 perſons were to be fed in each of thoſe Colledges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereas their yearly Revenues was ſcarcely ſufficient for eight Maſters.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:62701:30"/> 13. The Vow of obedience with which they tye themſelves to the Pope, doth not oblige them to be more faithful to externes, then to us. Neither is there in that Vow any thing contrary to the Oath which they will ſwear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me. They will attempt nothing (I am ſure) againſt their Prince. That Vow to the Pope bindeth them to go to barbarous and ſavage Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that they may reduce them to the Catholick Church. The whole World teſtifyeth that the remoteſt Regions of the <hi>Indies,</hi> together with infinite Hereticks, have been by their pains and learned endeavours, brought to Chriſts fold. I remember I have often ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that if the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of Spaniſh Fathers be ſo profitable for <hi>Spain,</hi> why ſhould not <hi>France</hi> with reaſon expect the ſame? Is that Kingdom more fortunate and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing than this? <hi>Spain</hi> is loved by the Spaniards, and why ſhould the <hi>French</hi> hate their Native ſoil?</p>
            <p n="14">14. But as you are wont to ſay, theſe men ſeek to be admitted into Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces and Kingdomes what way ſoever they can. Pray you is this an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence? 'Tis the cuſtom of all that follow the inſtinct of nature. I my ſelf, by what means I could, ſought to get my Crown. Howſoever we cannot but admire the Fathers conſtant patience, whereby they go through ſo great and hard matters, and bear ſo many and ſo heavy Croſſes.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Neither do I eſteem them the worſe, for that they be ſo obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of their Rules and Conſtitutions. This is that whereby the Society doth increaſe, flouriſh and better it ſelf every day more and more. For this Reaſon I thought not good to change any of their Conſtitutions and Rules, though I have made ſome change in others, which was not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of all. But that's no matter.</p>
            <p n="16">16. The Fathers of the Society have many back Freinds, among ſome that ſeem Holy and Religious Perſons, who ſpeak ill of them. This no wiſe man will wonder at. Our age is not come to that Sanctity, that Ignorance ſhould ceaſs to hate Learning, or corruption of manners leave to envy integrity of life. It was ſo in times paſt, and ſo 'tis ſtill. Theſe Moaths are alwayes gnawing on learned works. No proſperity ſo circumſpect that can ſcape the tooth of malice, hatred and envy, alwayes attend the higheſt things. I obſerved: when it was conſulted about the recalling of the Ieſuits into <hi>France,</hi> that two ſorts of men did ſpecially oppoſe themſelves, Hereticks, and looſe living Church-men: the one was moved thereunto by their bad
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62701:30"/> Faith, the other by their bad Life. But I am ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hereby moved to alter my intended purpoſe, that I am more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in my reſolution.</p>
            <p n="17">17. The Fathers of the Society, ſpeak and think honourably of the Pope, ſo they ſhould, and ſo do I; I joyn with them, ſince I am certain that, in averring and defending the Popes authority, they differ not from other Catholick Divines.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Neither did their Doctrine ever give occaſion to Clergy men to deny me tribute. Nor is there any to be found, whom theſe Fathers Words or Books animated to killing of Kings. VVhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſome have patcht together to bring them to Diſcredit, is all a Fiction and meer Fable. Thirty Years and more are paſſed, ſince the Fathers began to instruct the Youth of <hi>France</hi> both in Vertue and Learning. Of theſe ſame have gone through with all their Studies in their Schools. Others have broke off, and applied themſelves to Phyſick or Law. Tell me whether any of thoſe ever learnt of their Maſters to lay hands upon Kings, and kill them? I tell You the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are ſo clear, that they are content to appeal even to their own Enemies judgement. There are ſome Pulpit-Men among the Heriticks, who were trained up in the Fathers Schools: Ask theſe Men their judgements concerning the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits Lives and Doctrine: But whoſe Cauſe is ſo good as to deſire to be tryed by Enemies? Yet I am ſure in their Caſe this has been done, The Miniſters have been asked their judgement of the Ieſuits: And they have given no other Anſwor, but, That the Ieſuits Lives cannot be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and for their Doctrine, that it is in too cear a Sunne to be questioned. Cerces few can be found that will dare to ſtand to their Enemies judgement, their ſecurity of Conſcience muſt needs be great, that fears not any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries Verdict.</p>
            <p n="19">19. The Confeſſion of <hi>Barriere,</hi> who atttempted ſomething against my Perſon, doth not infringe that which I have ſaid. For ſo far was any Ieſuit from that fact (which you nevertheleſs affirm) that one of theſe Fathers of good credit adviſed me of it in time, and another of them
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62701:31"/> dehorted and deterred <hi>Barriere</hi> from his attempt, propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to him Gods heavy Iudgements due to ſuch Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours.</p>
            <p n="20">20. As for <hi>Chaſtel,</hi> all imaginable torments, were not able to wreſt the leaſt Word againſt <hi>Varadius</hi> or any one Father of the Society. If this be not ſo, why ſpared you the guilty? Why let you them go when you had them faſt? why puniſhed you them not according to your Law and Court?</p>
            <p n="21">21. But to grant you that that never was; ſuppoſe ſome one of the Society had attempted againſt my Perſon. Will you condemn all the Apoſtles for one <hi>Judas?</hi> ſhall the puniſhment light on my head, for whatſoever any of my Souldiers ſhall treſpaſs in military licenſe? I acknowledge the hand of God, whoſe will it was to have me preſſed and humbled at that time; the ſame hand raiſed me and ſet me ſafe again. Gods goodneſs and providence be thanked. I have learnt to forget and forgive injuries for Gods ſake, as I willingly do for that King, who is greater then my ſelf. And now I will be ſo far from remembring injuries done unto me or revenging the ſame, that I will daily offer up Prayers to God for my Enemies. All of us have need of Gods mercy, which is no wayes better to be obtained, than by prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and readily pardoning thoſe who have offended us.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="letter">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:62701:31"/>
            <head>The Fourth LETTER, <hi>That the Jeſuits are neither Factious, nor Enemies to Biſhops.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. SR. There ſeems to be an indiſpenſable neceſſity that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences ſhould ſometimes ariſe amongſt Gods Servants; for where there are different intereſts, as it falls out in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers communities, it is hardly poſſible, but there will be claſhing now and then to maintain them, and the Divel will be ſure to blow the coales of diſſention to widen the breach. Saints upon earth have had their controverſies: Witneſs St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Barnaby,</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul, [Acts</hi> 5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.] St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and S. <hi>Hierom.</hi> And the bleſſed Angels in Heaven are recorded in holy Scripture to have reſiſted one another, when they did not clearly underſtand Gods will; as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned between the two Angel-Gardians of the Jews and the Perſians, who ſtood each of them for their Pupils, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one another for the ſpace of one and twenty <note place="margin">
                  <hi>St. Hier. Theodor. S. Greg. S. Thom. apud Cornel. a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid. Daniel.</hi> 10.</note> dayes; the Angel of the Jews ſtriving for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, leaſt they ſhould be corrupted and perverted by thoſe Infidels; and the Angel of the Perſians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving their ſtay, that the Perſians by converſing with them might be converted to the true Faith. What wonder then if frail men are ſometimes at variance, when both parties take themſelves to have right on their ſides. This has been more then once the caſe between Regulars and Seculars, to diſpute exemptions and priviledges, while neither of them will yield what they conceive to be their due, till their Supream Paſtor pronounce the ſentence, and take up the diſpute. But why the Jeſuits ſhould bare the blame of thoſe misfortunes more than others. I do not ſee; only they are Jeſuits, and therefore muſt have the cheif hand in all manner of miſcheif, if their enemies may be credited.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:62701:32"/>
            <p> Sect. 9. 2. In the firſt place, Dr. <hi>St.</hi> objects the differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Jeſuits and the Secular Prieſts, begun (ſaies he) at <hi>Wisbich</hi> Caſtle. But he is much out of his ſtory, for the Jeſuits had no hand in the breach, as is clearely to be ſeen in <hi>Mores</hi> Hiſtory [<hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>l,</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 17.] Some diſpute indeed there was, upon Mr. <hi>George Blackwels</hi> being eſtabliſhed Superiour over the Clergy, under the title of Arch-prieſt &amp; if Fa. <hi>Parſons</hi> ſtood up in defence of his Holineſs authority in that occaſion, he ought not to be blamed for it, but I will never beleive that he uſed ſuch ſcolding reproachful language, as the Dr. ſpeaks of out of <hi>Watſon,</hi> nor indeed half ſo foul language as is to be found in his own works. Had he call'd it <hi>Folly,</hi> or a <hi>Bad ſpirit,</hi> to reſiſt the Popes Authority, he were not to be blamed, Sir, calling things by their own names, no more than the Apoſtle, for his character of thoſe of <hi>Candia,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n his time. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 12. But that you may ſee how unlucky the Dr. is in his Authors, this <hi>Watſon</hi> was ecuted at Tyburn for having a hand in Sir <hi>Walter Rawleighs</hi> buſineſs, and dyed very penitent, retracting with great korror what he had paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately written againſt the Jeſuits, and in particular againſt Fa. <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> But F. <hi>Parſons</hi> was the man that hindred the Clergy from have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Biſhop. No ſuch matter. There is a writing of his to be ſeen, in which he gave his Holnieſs nine reaſons for the conveniency and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of having two Biſhops in <hi>England,</hi> and a Letter to Cardinal <hi>Alan</hi> about their maintenance. What the Dr. inſinuates of the Jeſuits aim to govern the Clergy is as wide of truth. Tis far from their ſpirit and vocation to ſeek any ſuch authority, or to pretend any more then to be their fellow-labourers in the Engliſh vineyard, as ſent thither by the ſame common Maſter, Chriſts Vicar upon earth, for the good of ſouls.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He enlarges himſelf yet more upon another later controverſy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Regulars and Seculars, about the Biſhop of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> and makes a long Catalogue of books writ <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> and it is no diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to the Jeſuits to ſee <hi>Aurelius</hi> named amongſt their Adverſaries who they ſay proved afterwards to be that famous Janſeniſt the Abbot of St. <hi>Cyran.</hi> But becauſe <hi>Urban</hi> the eight, has commanded under cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that no more ſhould be written of that ſubject, I forbear to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with it. Only, Sir, you may pleaſe to take notice how ignorantly the Dr. ſays, the Pope only ſuppreſſed the books on both ſides, but <hi>durſt not interpoſe at all in the main buſineſs, for fear of loſing either ſide.</hi> For was not the main controverſy about the regulars juriſdiction, and the validity of confeſſions heard by them, without the Biſhops appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation? And did not his Holines in his <hi>Breve A. D.</hi> 1631. as is to be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62701:32"/> ſeen in <hi>Mores</hi> Hiſtory, [<hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>l</hi> 10. <hi>an.</hi> 9.] declare all ſuch confeſſions valid, and that Regulars having their power immediately from the Sea Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, needed no Epiſcopal approbation to hear confeſſions. And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that all Miſſioners were to uſe their faculties and priviledges in the ſame manner as they did in <hi>Gregory</hi> 13. and <hi>Paul</hi> 5. time. Let the Dr. then for ſhame forbear to cry out as he doth; <hi>were not here controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies to be determined? to what purpoſe is that authority that dare not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed when there is need of it?</hi> You ſee the Pope durſt <hi>interpoſe</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercſe his authority</hi> and <hi>determine</hi> the main <hi>controverſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect</hi> 10. 4. His third objection is the Jeſuits particular oppoſition againſt Biſhops<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but they have a ready anſwer, <hi>we have no ſuch cuſtome nor the Church of God.</hi> 1 Cor. 11. They do not deny but they have had their difficulties with ſome Biſhops about their Priviledges, which you'l ſay they have no reaſon to forgo, but have no <hi>ſpite to their authority,</hi> as the Dr. maliciouſly affirms. I told you before how Father <hi>Parſons</hi> laboured to have <hi>Catholick</hi> Biſhops ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled in <hi>England,</hi> now I will give you a later Teſtimony, how far they are from oppoſing any ſuch authority in a part of their Provinciall let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, 4. <hi>Decemb. A. D.</hi> 1635. <hi>[Morus ibid. an.</hi> 9.] to the Pope's <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio</hi> then reſident with the Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en of <hi>England. None of ours,</hi> ſays he, <hi>has ever oppoſed himſelf againſt the eſtabliſhment of Epiſcopal authority, but we have either delivered our opinions, when we were askt by thoſe that had power to do it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or have written by conſtraint, what we judged neceſſary to defend the faith and dignity of the Sea Apoſtolick for which no body can blame us. Nor were we heretofore any let or hinderance to the Biſhop of</hi> Calcedon, <hi>or will we be hereafter to any other, from freely exerciſing whatſoever power he ſhall receive from the Sea Apoſtolick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to the Drs. two inſtances, of the Jeſuits unworthy dealing, with the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Manille</hi> and Biſhop of <hi>Angelopolis:</hi> I confeſs it is a hard task, to convince a Lyar, that fetches his news out of another World, many will rather chuſe to believe him, then go ſo far to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove him. Yet in our caſe, the very Authors themſelves, out of whom he has copyed his ſtories, render them nor only ſuſpected but improbable: he might as well have taken them out ot the <hi>Holland</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zet, which is uſually well furniſhed with ſuch matters. All I have to ſay to that of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Manille,</hi> is to tell you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the Moral Practiſe of the Jeſuits, is juſt ſuch another Libell as the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Jeſuitiſm, and both burnt at <hi>Paris</hi> by the Hangman, in obedience to the Kings Orders, though it ſeems, they have riſen again out of their Aſhes, and appear in <hi>London</hi> like <hi>Phoenixes.</hi> The journall of St. <hi>Amour</hi> with the other ſtory of the Biſhop of <hi>Angelopolis,</hi> is as little to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62701:33"/> be credited as having had the ſame fate to be deſtroyed by the Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and who will truſt a rank Janſeniſt, when he writes againſt his profeſſed enemies the Jeſuits. But I have ſomething more to ſay to him and his ſtory: for I have lately met with a writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Father <hi>Annats,</hi> who has clearly lay'd open his <note place="margin">Fauſſetez &amp; Impoſtures d'un Cahier, &amp;c.</note> manifeſt impoſtures, and proved the whole Machine of his accuſations, to be ſuch a tottering Ruinous piece, and ſo ill contrived, that it falls to the ground at the leaſt touch. This you will preſently ſee if you pleaſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that all is built upon a letter, of the Biſhop of <hi>Angelopolis</hi> to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>10th.</hi> which no wiſe man will believe, was ever written by the Biſhop, but forged at <hi>Port Royal,</hi> as there is juſt reaſon to ſuſpect; For the publiſher was ſo ſtrangely blinded with paſſion, to diſgrace the Jeſuits, he did not mind, that his accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would ſerve them for a very ſufficient anſwer. He makes the Biſhop of <hi>Angelopolis</hi> complain, how ſhamfully he was abuſed by the Jeſuits of his <hi>Dioceſſe.</hi> I confeſs the word of a Biſhop carries a great authority: but what if a greater Biſhop than he were of a contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y mind? will it not much leſſen his credit? this is our caſe; for the ſame Biſhop of <hi>Angelopolis,</hi> in the ſame letter, confeſſes the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mexico,</hi> ſtood wholy for the Jeſuits. What if beſides this Arch-Biſhop, the <hi>Vice Roy,</hi> and all the Kings Officers and Judges of his Courts, were alſo for the Jeſuits? What if all the Religious of other Orders, and the Inquiſtors, nay his own Chapter, all ſided with the Jeſuits? Will not all theſe grave Teſtimonies be able to clear them? The Biſhop again profeſſes in the ſame letter, that the Jeſuits had gained all theſe to their party, and that <hi>he</hi> was <hi>alone.</hi> What ſhall we then think of a Letter, which in the ſame breath, both accuſes and defends the Jeſuits, and ſo defends them, that the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer himſelf acknowledges he is <hi>alone,</hi> againſt the whole Soveraign Eccleſiaſtical and ſecular power of the Country? is it not a very pleaſant continuance, that to make the Jeſuits criminal, all the moſt honourable and conſiderable Perſons of the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> muſt be made their Complices and guilty of the ſame Crime? Beleive me, had the Jeſuits ſtood with the Biſhop againſt all thoſe, Doctor <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> would have cryed out as loud againſt them.</p>
            <p>Another ground to ſuſpect, the Biſhops Letter was forged, is the improbability of the accuſations: For who will eaſily believe, that the Jeſuits either bribed the Vice Roy, or offered a ſum of money
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62701:33"/> for the Biſhops head, or forced him into the Mountains, or put their Scholars in Maſcarade to abuſe him, or refuſed to obey the Popes or the Kings orders, or preach'd Chriſt ſo as to conceal his crucifixion, or cauſed other regulars to be whipp'd and baniſhed that came into <hi>China,</hi> or that they were ſo ſtrangely fallen from their firſt Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute as to need a Reformation. Methinks the Publiſher of theſe Accuſations (and the Dr. too who takes them up at ſecond hand) might have done well to have reflected, on that judicious Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an old German Proteſtant, who when he heard what ſtrange tales were told of the Jeſuits, and amongſt the reſt Cardinal that <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> had in his time raviſhed I know not how many Virgins. Such Reports ſaith he, are of no advantage to our Cauſe; for when the World is once uſed to ſuch improbable Lyes, they will hardly be brought after to believe what is really true.</p>
            <p>However the Publiſher ſticks not only to relate them but alſo to aſſure us, that the Popes Breve 16. <hi>April Anno Dom.</hi> 1648. fully <hi>confirmes</hi> whatever the Biſhop had objected againſt the Jeſuits, which is ſo notoriouſly falſe, that I wonder how he had the Face to ſay it, or the Dr. to repeat it after him. For in the whole Breve, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Congregation inſerted in it, there is not the leaſt mention made of any ſuch miſdemeanours of the Jeſuits, or any thing inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated to their diſparagement, but only a Declaration of ſome Points not derogating at all from thoſe Priviledges, which occaſioned the Controverſie, and a Reſolution of 26 doubts which is common to other Regulars as well as Jeſuits, and ſo little favourable to the Biſhops pretenſions, that Father <hi>Alvarade,</hi> the Jeſuits Procurator for <hi>Mexico</hi> not only proved 18 of the Reſolutions to be directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what he would have had, but alſo was permitted to Print if in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf. The World knows, Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the X, was not to an humour to diſſemble ſuch groſs abuſes, had they come to his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, a clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Argument (ſaies Father <hi>Annate)</hi> that the Ship that that brought the Letter from <hi>Mexico,</hi> delivered at <hi>Port Royal,</hi> or it it were eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> God heard his devout Pray'r that penn'd it, in which he <hi>beſeeches Chriſt Ieſus, that if what he writes does not aim at Gods glory it may never arrive at the Popes hands, or if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, he may not regard it but diſpiſe it.</hi> I know the Dr. talks ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Decree againſt the Jeſuits, but confeſſes it was put into the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex expurgatorius</hi> by <hi>Alexander</hi> the 7th. which is a ſhrewd ſign it was a ſurreptitious or counterfeit: Peice which his Holineſs would not own. I am ſure, there is nothing againſt the Jeſuits, in the final determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62701:34"/> of the whole controverſie, ſigned by Cardinal <hi>Spadae,</hi> who was head of that Congregation <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1652. after ſix years diſpute; for never could<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Congregation be drawn, to declare the validity of the Biſhops excommunications, or the Jeſuits neceſſity of being abſolv'd from them, or to condemn the Jeſuits carriage in that whole buſineſs. On the contrary ſide, I find both Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſpeak very honourably of them; for this laſt ſtyles the Society a <hi>laudable and profitable Order,</hi> that <hi>Labours</hi> with great <hi>Fruit</hi> of Souls, and exhorts the Biſhops to <hi>embrace</hi> them as ſuch. And that which was in 1648 concludes thus. <hi>The Holy Congregation ſeriouſly exhorts in our Lord, and admoniſhes the Biſhop that being mindful of Chriſtian meekneſs, he carry himſelf with a Fatherly affection towards the Society of Ieſus, which according to their laudable inſtitute has laboured, and ſtill continually labours with ſo much Fruit in the Church of God. And that conſidering it as a profitable help, in the conduct of his Church, he treat them favourably and return to his former Freindſhip,</hi> &amp;c. Note that the Tranſlator of the <hi>Breve</hi> where this is recited, could not abide to ſee ſo clear a Teſtimony of the Jeſuits good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, actually performed for Gods Church. What does he? accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Ianſenian</hi> dialect, he turns the word <hi>Labor at</hi> into <hi>Laborabat,</hi> and ſo tranſlates it in the Preterimperfect tenſe, to make his Reader beleive, that though the Congregation acknowledge, the Jeſuits have formerly done the Church good ſervice, yet all that is paſt and gone, whereas the Congregation ſpeaks expreſly in the Preſent tenſe, that they ſtill labour without intermiſſion: So far were thoſe grave Prelates it ſeems, from thinking there was any need of reforming the Jeſuits, as was objected. I may add unto all this one reflexion more, which might ſerve alone, to juſtifie the Jeſuits in their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with the Biſhop. Know then that the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Counſel in <hi>India,</hi> being throughly inform'd of all paſſages in thoſe Countries, thought fit for the quiet and peace of his Dioceſs, to recal the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to <hi>Madrid,</hi> and there make him reſign up his Biſhoprick of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelopolis,</hi> and content himſelf with another leſs Biſhoprick in new <hi>Spain,</hi> which is a ſign, he had not carried himſelf with ſo much ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction as was expected.</p>
            <p>I muſt not leave this point without clearing the Jeſuits way of Preaching and Converting Souls in <hi>China.</hi> This I cannot do better, then by producing the Teſtimony of a learned and grave Dominican, who lived long in that Kingdom, and was well acquainted with the Jeſuits, who by the way, it ſeems uſed him civilly for all he was of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62701:34"/> another Order, and did not cauſe him to be whipped or baniſhed, as their cuſtom is if we beleive Dr. <hi>Stil. I Brother Dominious Sar-Petrus alias of St.</hi> Peter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sicilian of the Order of Preachers, heretofore</hi> &amp;c. <hi>do declare unto all thoſe, that ſhall ſee theſe preſent Letters. Firſt, That having been ſent by my Superiours to Preach in this Kingdom, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by their command, for</hi> 8 <hi>years, diligently informed my ſelf of all the ſuperſtitions of their Sects, do judge, that the practiſe, which the Fathers miſſionants of the Society of Ieſus make profeſſion to follow, in diſpenſing with certain Ceremonies, with which the Chriſtians in</hi> China, <hi>uſe to honour their Philoſopher</hi> Confuſius, <hi>and their other deceaſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours, is not only ſafe (as approved by the</hi> H. <hi>Congregation of the Univerſal Inquiſition) but if we regard the Principles of their prime Sects, much more probable then the contrary, and not only profitable but alſo neceſſary, to open the Gate of the Goſpel to thoſe Heathens,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Secondly, I atteſt that the Fathers of the Society in this Kingdom of</hi> China, <hi>announce Christ cruciſied unto the Pagans not only by word of mouth, but in their many writings, and diligently inſtruct their Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyts in the myſteries of the ſacred Paſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in ſome Reſidences have erected confraternities of the holy Paſſion, and that of late the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor of our holy Law call'd</hi> Yan Quam Sein, <hi>urged this cheifly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Preachers of the Goſpel, that they worſhiped a man cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, for the Lord of Heaven and Earth, which he proved out of the Books of the Fathers of the ſociety, &amp;c. Thirdly, I attest, and for as much as it is neceſſary, do confirm it by Oath, that in giving theſe two Atteſtations, I was not led by any bodies intreaty or perſwaſion, but onely by the love of Truth. For conſidering that the doubts which are moved in theſe matters, are onely in point of Fact (as the Congregation inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates) and that in ſuch moral things, the circumſtances of the Fact, are to be meaſured by the judgement of learned and prudent men: It ſeemed to me very unreaſonable, to condemn as ſuperſtitious, what ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſo great Miſſioners of the ſociety (with whom I have lived and familiarly converſed theſe</hi> 3 <hi>years, whoſe Charity I have experienced, and whoſe Learning, Piety, Zeal, good Behaviour, not to ſay holineſs, is well known to me) and ſo many of their worthy Predeceſſours, have judged to belong only to a politick and civilkind of worſhip. Wherefore knowing that upon occaſion of certain doubts, that Fr.</hi> Br. John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſta de Morales, <hi>of the ſame Order and Province,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>propounded to the holy Cougregation of the univerſal inquiſition</hi> Anno Dom. 1645. <hi>ſome not well affected to the Society, both in</hi> Europe <hi>and</hi> India, <hi>have given out; that the Miſſionanes of the Society, in the Kingdom of</hi> China,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62701:35"/> 
               <hi>did not Preach Chriſt crucified, and permitted their Chriſtians to play the Idolators that I may not by my ſilence, ſeem to conſent to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and that I may with all as much as I can, clear the reputation of ſo great Fathers, I have given this Teſtimony, ſubmitting it to the more certain judgement of the holy</hi> Roman <hi>Church. In Witneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I have given theſe Letters, and ſigned them with my own Hand, in this Houſe of</hi> Canton, <hi>where we are kept in baniſhment and thraldom, for the true Faith</hi> 4. Aug. Anno Dom. 1668. <hi>B. Dominicus Sar Patrus,</hi> &amp;c. I find this Atteſtation, in Latin, in <hi>Eſtrix</hi> his <hi>Diatriba Theologica</hi> newly printed at <hi>Antwerp</hi> [1 pag. 241.] and the Author who reſides at <hi>Lovain,</hi> is ready to ſhew an authentical Copy, faithfully taken out of the original, which is kept in the Jeſuits atchievments at <hi>Rome.</hi> And I need go no farther, to confute all the Drs. ſlaunders, of the Jeſuites behaviour in <hi>China;</hi> for what he ſaies of the 17 Decrees againſt the Jeſuits 1645. they were the Anſwers to <hi>Morales</hi> his doubts mentioned in this Atteſtation, but nothing againſt the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, as appears by the latter Decree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſame Congregation under <hi>Alexander</hi> the 7th. 1656.</p>
            <p>Sect. 11. His laſt Objection is about the Jeſuits differences in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Doctrine, for he ſaies truly they not only diſſent from the Janſeniſts in the five known Propoſitions, but alſo differ from the Dominicans in two man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oints, the immaculate conception of our bleſſed Lady and Phyſical Predeterminations. Sir, this Objection concerns other Catholick Drs. as well as the Jeſuits, for they all agree with the Jeſuits that the five <hi>Ianſenian</hi> Propoſitions condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Holineſs are heretical, and many of them ſide alſo with the Jeſuits againſt the Dominicans, in the other two Controverſies yet under debate. However becauſe the Jeſuits are particularly named by the Dr. as the chief Diſſenters, you may expect a word or two from me in their juſtification. It is their glory to have ſo ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſed the <hi>Ianſeniſts</hi> Doctrine, which has been ſince blaſted by the definitive Sentence of the Supream Paſtors of the Church. The Dr. might as well have objected their diſſenting from the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> for ſince his Holineſs his cenſure has been generally received by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks all over Chriſtendom, there can be no queſtion but <hi>Ianſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme</hi> is condemned by the Church, as well as <hi>Calviniſme,</hi> and are both equally to be eſteemed Hereſie, for I ſuppoſe we all agree that the whole Church cannot erre in condemning Hereſie, and when we ſay ſo, our meaning muſt be not to include the oppoſite Party, or to require that they ſubmit and <hi>declare that they believe contrary</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:62701:35"/> 
               <hi>to what they beleived before,</hi> as the Dr. ſeems to require, pag. 447. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we may juſtify the <hi>Arians</hi> and all other Hereticks, who were rarely known to have ſubmited to the judgment of the Church that condemn'd them, though aſſembled in general Councils. It is clear then that ſuch <hi>diviſions</hi> as theſe between the Church and thoſe that <hi>ſeperate</hi> themſelves from her, are not prejudicial to the Church's Unity, which is entirely preſerved by a due ſubmiſſion of all her members unto what the Church thinks fit to determine. It were eaſy here to anſwer the Drs. queſtion; <hi>let them name one controverſy that has been ended in their Church, meerly by the Pope's decrees;</hi> for to go no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this very controverſy of the Janſeniſts <hi>has been ended by the Popes decrees,</hi> and ſo ended that the Janſeniſts themſelves have ſubmitted to them, as is evident to all thoſe that are not ignorant in thoſe affairs; for did they not (the Biſhops as well as others, that had ſtood out ſo long) at laſt ſubmit and ſign the <hi>Formulaire,</hi> by which they not only acknowledged the 5 condemned Propoſitions to be Heretical, but to be the very propoſitions of <hi>Ianſenius,</hi> and did not his Holineſs upon the <hi>French</hi> Kings declaration of this their ſubmiſſion, by a particular <hi>Breve,</hi> reſtore peace to the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church?</p>
            <p>How ſhamefully then does the Dr. cry out; <hi>that there never was a fairer occaſion given to the Pope, to ſhew his authority for preſervation of the Church's vnity, then this of the ſive propoſitions.</hi> And yet <hi>that he could never be prevailed with to ſuffer the main controverſy to be touch't,</hi> and that <hi>there are ſo many wayes to avade his deffinitions, that his Authority ſignifies nothing:</hi> for you ſee for all the Janſeniſts <hi>ways</hi> and <hi>tricks to evade,</hi> the Pope <hi>ſhewed his authority to preſerve the Churches unity,</hi> and was <hi>prevail'd with</hi> to define the <hi>main controverſy</hi> ſo far; that no body now dare call it in queſtion or pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelf a <hi>Ianſeniſt,</hi> whatſoever he may be in his heart. But why ſays he, does not the Pope, or at leaſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Concils</hi> put an end to all controverſies amongſt Catholicks? For example<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> why does he not determine the differences about the <hi>Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Conception and Predetermination,</hi> which have made ſo great a noiſe in the world? Let him firſt tell me, why did not our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour leave all matters of Faith ſo clearly expreſt in holy Scriptures, as to prevent all diſputes amongſt Chriſtians, or why did not the firſt four general <hi>Councils</hi> (whoſe Authority the Dr. allows) give us a clear Comment upon all difficult places which are found in the ſacred Text, or why does not Dr. <hi>St.</hi> himſelf, undertake out of Scripture, to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile all the diſſenting members of his Church, for ſince <hi>all parties agree the Scripture to be Infallible</hi> (it is his own rule) <hi>there can be no more</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:62701:36"/> 
               <hi>certain way for Unity.</hi> Why I ſay does he not then, make uſe of this <hi>moſt certain way</hi> to keep unity in his Church, where we ſee they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn one another of damnable errours? I will not take upon me to enter into the ſecret Counſels of Chriſt, and his holy Spouſe the Church, or to give you the reaſons why they thought fit to leave things as they are. But I may venture to gueſs why the Dr. with all his writing and preaching, has not yet, nor never will void all controverſies out of Scripture; for where the difficulty lyes in the ſence of Scripture, it ſelf (as it is our caſe) let it be never ſo infallible, there cannot be a leſs certain way to Unity, or more endleſs way of taking up diſputes; then the Scripture, unleſs it would ſpeak for it ſelf, and declare its own meaning, which will never be. It is not ſo with Catholicks, for the Pope or a General Council, can declare their own meaning, if there be any doubt of it, as it happened in the caſe of the five Propſitions, which the Janſeniſts would have drawn into different ſenſes, for his Holineſs found a way to make them clearly underſtand his meaning. And I think there never was Heretick condemned in a general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, that doubted whether he were condemn'd or no, as Proteſtants doubt, whether Infants may be Baptized, whether Biſhops are <hi>de jure Divino,</hi> &amp;c. For all their infallible Scriptures. To maintain Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be a better way to decide controverſies, then the living Voice of the Church, is juſt as if a man ſhould contend, that the Law it ſelf or God Almighty is a better means to end Suits at Law then the Judges upon the Bench; for while the Law and God Almighty are ſilent, unleſs the Judge pronounce ſentence, the Suite muſt of neceſſity be endleſs, and ſo muſt all controverſies in Religions; for all the infallibility of Scripture, ſo long as it does not explicate its own meaning, and anſwer all difficulties.</p>
            <p>As for the diſputes between the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> and the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> about predetermination and the Immaculate Conception, it is ſtrange ſuch School diſputes ſhould be ſtill objected againſt the unity of our Church. I ſay School diſputes for ſo I muſt call them, till the Church pleaſe to determin them, for the Dr. muſt know, that though theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are about matters of Faith <hi>in reality,</hi> yet are they not mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith <hi>quo ad nos,</hi> till they be propoſed unto us as ſuch, and therefore although we contend about them, and are at variance among our ſelves, yet our unity is ſtill preſerved by this, that both parties are ready to ſubmit their judgments to the judgment of the Church, when ever ſhe pleaſes to deliver the truth.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:62701:36"/>
            <p> If this had been well conſidered by the Dr. he would not have taken ſo much pains to prove ſo great a Paradox, as that there is as much union amongſt Proteſtants as Roman-Catholicks. In the interim the Church is careful to prevent all inconveniences, which ariſe, ſometimes out of the heat of ſuch eager diſputes by ſeverely forbidding both Parties to preſume to cenſure one anothers Tenets, and this under pain of excommunication and other penalties, for this amongſt obedient Children is ſufficient to keep them in Peace and Unity (for whatſoever they hold of the Popes infallibility) they all agree that obedience and ſubmiſſion is due to his Authority, upon pain of being accounted Schiſmaticks, for not yielding o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the common Paſtor and Head of the Church. Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants have no ſuch way either to ſuſpend or end their diſputes, but muſt of neceſſity wrangle it out to the Worlds end, for want of a living Judge of Controverſies. What the Dr. adds of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits holding a ſtrange opinion of the Popes infallibility in matters of Fact, is moſt falſe, for they differ not from any other Catholick Divines, as I have often told you. Laſtly, for their <hi>perſwading the People to defend the immaculate Conception with Fire and Sword and with their Blood,</hi> with which he concludes his <hi>5th.</hi> Chapter, it needs no Anſwer; his Author has no credit as having been burnt at <hi>Paris</hi> for a Libel by the Kings order, as I have told you. And now I promiſe you I will tire you no more with my long Letters, having clearly and freely given you my ſentiments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all the Drs. ſlaunders and objections againſt the Jeſuits,</p>
            <trailer>Farewel.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:62701:37"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi> I have yet a Word or two to add upon the Receipt &amp; Peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of two Books ſince the writing of this Letter. The firſt is a compendious Account of the miſſion of <hi>China</hi> given at <hi>Rome</hi> this very Year 1672. to the ſacred Congregation, <hi>de propagandà fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> by Father <hi>Proſper Intercetta</hi> the Jeſuits Procurator from that Kingdom. By this it appears that the Jeſuits do not alwayes find that <hi>commodious entertainment</hi> in <hi>China,</hi> which the Dr. dreams of; for this Author witneſſes that they commonly beg their ſuſtenance of Neighbouring Europeans, and have not been without their Perſecutions. For <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1664 four of them were clapt up cloſe Priſoners, with three Chains, a piece tyed to their Necks, three to their Hands, and three to their Feet: the cheif of theſe F. <hi>Adam</hi> was ſentenc'd to a cruel death (though the Execution was hinder'd by a terrible Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, and other dreadful ſigns from Heaven, which made the People cry out, <hi>(great is the God of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,)</hi> the other three were condemned to have 40 Baſtinadoes and all the reſt were forc'd out of their 41 Reſidences, and 159 Churches and baniſhed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto Cantons, and there kept Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, nor have we yet news of their Releaſement, though the laſt Letters from <hi>Pekin</hi> of the 23 <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1670. give great hopes of more liberty, then ever to Preach our Chriſtian Faith, ſince the honourable Reception of the <hi>Portugal</hi> Embaſſadour in that Court. It alſo appears to be falſe what the Dr. affirms of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religious, being kept out of the Kingdom by the Ieſuits, for the ſame Author tells us that before the late perſecution, the Dominicans had 21 Churches and 11 Reſidences, and the Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcans 3 Churches and 1 Reſidence. Laſtly, this Author rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons up 254980 converted by the Ieſuits alone, from the Year 1581. to 1667. (not <hi>from Laces and Ribbands,)</hi> but from Idolatry, to the worſhip of <hi>Chriſt crucified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other Book I mentioned contains a ſecond Anſwer to the imfamous pretended Letter of the Biſhop of <hi>Angelopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:62701:37"/> drawn out of his Annotations upon St. <hi>Tereſa's</hi> ſpiritual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, tranſlated out of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> by <hi>Francis Pellicot</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner and Confeſſour in the Queens Court, and Printed in <hi>Paris</hi> by <hi>George Joſſe</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Thornes.</hi> For there the Tranſlator (who profeſſes an intimate acquaintance with the ſaid Biſhop) in his Preface, does not only deny him to have been Author of that ſcandalous Letter to the Pope, but produces three other Letters of his, written ſome Years after his conteſt with the Ieſuits, highly in their commendation, as you may ſee when you pleaſe. And farther in the Biſhops life, he ſhews how he retracted what he had unadviſedly done againſt them, in oppoſing their Priviledges out of the Biſhops own words which here follow. <hi>We are often ſo wedded to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Palafox Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. to the</hi> 56 <hi>Ep. of St.</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſa.</note> 
               <hi>falſe perſwaſions, which ſelf Love ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts to maintain a bad Cauſe, that it is hard to root them out of our ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and reduce our ſelves to the truth. This evil is very familiar with us, and I dayly experience it in my ſelf, and particularly in a certain Cauſe; for why ſhould I not publickly acknowledge my Errour, ſince I offended in the ſight of the whole World. I ſay it happened in a thing of this nature, that I found certain Reaſons to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my Adverſaries</hi> (the Ieſuits) <hi>which ſeem'd to me good and holy, but really were not ſo, but the effects of a vain and preſumptuous Spirit. For I found afterwards, with the help of divine light, that the thing which I believed was from God, was quite contrary to his ſervice. And this falſe belief of mine ſprung from my ſelf love, my paſſion, my pride, my vanity and my preſumption.</hi> What better Apology can be made for the Ieſuits, than this humble Confeſſion and Retractation of the Biſhop?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
